<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>External references</title>
</header>

<body>

<section>
  <title>Related Software Projects</title>

  <table class="noborder">

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="https://bitbucket.org/travis_bear/grinder_to_graphite">Grinder to Graphite</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
        Grinder to Graphite (g2g) is a tool that analyzes the logs
        from your Grinder tests, and sends the data into Graphite
        where it can be visualized in a variety of ways.
      </td>
    </tr>
    
    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="https://github.com/DealerDotCom/grinder-groovy">grinder-groovy</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
	Alternative script engine for The Grinder: write your test scripts in Groovy.
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="ext:grinder-groovy">Grinder maven plugin</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
	A Maven Plugin for The Grinder, with Grinder Analyzer
	integration. The plugin allows you to run The Grinder from a
	Maven build, and analyse the results.
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="ext:ngrinder">nGrinder</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
     A web based testing framework built on top of The Grinder. The
     demo video is particularly slick.
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="ext:grinder-webtest">Grinder Webtest</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
     This custom module allows execution of Visual Studio <em>webtest</em> files.
     It supports parameterization, capturing of variables in HTTP responses, and
     response validation using regular expressions. Test scripts may be logically
     grouped into test sets, allowing them to share variables and captured values.
     Test sets can be run sequentially, randomly, in a specific thread, or
     according to a percentage-based weighting. A correlating test runner is
     also provided, making it easier for you to find and capture values in your
      HTTP responses.

     We have successfully used this module to run load tests of more than 300
     virtual users, with a scenario involving 21 different webtest scripts
     recorded in Fiddler.
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="ext:http-qat">HTTP Quality Assurance Toolkit</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
    HTTP functional and non-functional (load and performance)
    toolkit based on jython/grinder (http://grinder.sf.net)
    ...includes capabilities to support: SOA services, REST,
    json/xml encoding, AES and WS security ... and a stub to
    collect requests.
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="ext:grinder-agent-installer">The Grinder Agent Installer</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
    The Grinder Agent Installer is useful when you want to
    execute load tests in a heterogeneous context, and to
    simulate real users accessing the target application through
    a firewall, 3G, VPN, direct (router) and from different
    locales, where you haven't access to all this computers for
    run the agent.

    <p>It provides an installer any user can install and execute
    with only click next and provisioning some data in a graphic
    environment. You only have to wait the connections in the
    console.</p>
      </td>
    </tr>


    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="ext:grinder-in-the-cloud">Grinder In The Cloud</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
          Grinder in the Cloud leverages the well known Grinder load test
          framework by putting it in the cloud. It offers an easy to use load
          test framework with virtually unlimited firepower at a competitive
          price. This Windows based AMI starts the Grinder console. It starts
          Grinder agent AMIs to generate the load. The Agents automatically
          connect to the console. Built by Jörg Kalsbach.
      </td>
    </tr>


    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="ext:grinder-hudson">Grinder Plugin for Hudson</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
          This plug-in reads output result files from performance tests run
          with The Grinder, and will generate reports showing test results
          for every build and trend reports showing performance results across
          builds.
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="ext:ground-report">Ground Report</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
          The Ground Report is a collection of reporting utilities specific to
          The Grinder test tool.

          The tools consist of a reporting database and graphing &amp; report
          utilities based upon jyplot, jFreechart and DocBook written in Jython.
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="ext:grinder-analyzer">Grinder Analyzer</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
          Grinder Analyzer is a tool that parses log data from The Grinder and
          generates client-side performance graphs. These graphs include
          response time, transactions per second, and network bandwidth used.
          Like The Grinder itself, Grinder Analyzer uses Jython, and the
          excellent JFreechart graphing library.

        <figure src="images/grinder-analyzer.png" alt="Grinder Analyzer"
              width="328" height="230" />

      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="ext:webflange">webFlange</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
        webFlange is a continuous load testing web application written
        in Java. It leverages The Grinder for running tests, automatically
        creates reports and allows the creation of charts from the test
        results.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="site:grinderstone">GrinderStone</a>
      </td>

      <td></td>

      <td>
        GrinderStone is an Eclipse plug-in for Grinder load testing scripts
        development (debugger for scripts is included).
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Articles</title>

  <table class="noborder">


    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://agilegrind.blogspot.co.uk/">The Agile Grind</a>
      </td>

      <td>Gary Mulder's blog on using The Grinder.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://blackanvil.blogspot.com/2011/12/integrating-grinder-performance-data.html">Black Anvil: Visualizing Grinder Data With Other External Metrics</a>
      </td>

      <td>Using Graphite to visualise the test results.</td>
    </tr>


    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://vivin.net/tag/the-grinder/">Rough Book</a>
      </td>

      <td>A series of in-depth blog entries that introduce The Grinder and
          present a rich framework for scripts.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://www.performanceengineer.com/blog/introduction-to-the-grinder/">PerformanceEngineer.com: Introduction To The Grinder</a>
      </td>

      <td>An introductory blog entry showing how to set up The Grinder with <a href="site:grinderstone">GrinderStone</a>.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://www.pcpro.co.uk/features/230550/technology-you-can-bet-on/page3.html">PC Pro article</a>
      </td>

      <td>"Technology you can bet on" - Paddy Power uses The Grinder.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://www.infoq.com/news/2008/02/the-grinder-3">InfoQ News</a>
      </td>

      <td>Alexander Olaru interviews Philip Aston for InfoQ.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://tech.puredanger.com/2008/01/25/the-grinder-30-released/">Pure Danger Tech: The Grinder 3.0 Released</a>
      </td>

      <td>Alex Miller says some very nice things about The Grinder.

       <p class="quote">"...I was really pleasantly surprised by everything
       that I found. The Grinder has a fairly clean aesthetic that is hard to
       quantify but makes getting started a pleasant experience. What I found
       the most enjoyable about it was the use of Jython to script the actual
       test activity. <br/>

       ...It is trivial to start up the console and your agents, then have very
       fast modify / run cycles as nothing needs to be restarted. You just
       modify the test in your editor and hit play on the console. This allows
       you to very rapidly whip your test into shape.
       Kind of reminds me of Rails..."</p>

       </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://blackanvil.blogspot.com/2006/06/shootout-load-runner-vs-grinder-vs.html#links">The Black Anvil: Shootout: Load Runner vs The Grinder vs Apache JMeter</a>
      </td>

      <td>Detailed comparison of The Grinder, JMeter, and Load Runner from Travis Bear.

       <p class="quote">"...I recommended The Grinder as the tool to go forward
       with. It has a simple, clean UI that clearly shows what is going on
       without trying to do too much, and offers great power and simplicity
       with its unique Jython-based scripting approach. Jython allows complex
       scripts to be developed much more rapidly than in more formal languages
       like Java, yet it can access any Java library or class easily, allowing
       us to re-use elements of our existing work."</p>

         <p>Travis has since assisted with the implementation of slow socket support for The Grinder.</p>
       </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://cdjdn.com/downloads/performancetesting-grinder.pdf">Performance Testing using The Grinder</a>
      </td>

      <td>A high-level overview of test methodology using The Grinder from Paul Evans/Blue Slate Solutions. Hosted by the Capital District Java Developers Network.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://www.anser-e.com/testing/GrinderAutomationTutorial.html">Grinder Test Automation for the WebLogic Server</a>
      </td>

      <td>An custom automated test environment for WebLogic built on
      The Grinder.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a
        href="http://gashalot.com/writing/blog-grinder.php">Gash:
        Load Testing Java Applications</a>
      </td>
      <td>Replacing JMeter with The Grinder 3

       <p class="quote">"I went from a freshly downloaded tarball to
       fully functional test environment in about 2.5 hours. That's
       powerful."</p>
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki/wiki?TheGrinder">WikiWikiWeb</a>
      </td>

      <td>Entry on the Wiki of Wiki's.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://www.abcseo.com/papers/grinder.htm">Stress Testing with The Grinder and Cactus</a>
      </td>

      <td>Using The Grinder 2's JUnit plug-in with Cactus.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://dev2dev.bea.com/articles/aston.jsp">The Grinder: Load Testing for Everyone</a>
      </td>

      <td>An introductory article on The Grinder 2 from Phil Aston.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://www.anticlue.net/archives/000395.htm">Anticlue</a>
      </td>

      <td>Blog entry on The Grinder 3.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://www.oreillynet.com/pub/wlg/6743">Load Testing
        Web Services with Grinder</a>
      </td>

      <td>An article on testing Web Services with The Grinder 3.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://www.massivepropeller.com/users/austin/blogs/whatsnew/archive/000043.html">Massive Propeller: The Grinder</a>
      </td>

      <td>Blog entry on The Grinder 2.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://82.133.140.67/MrWorm/35">Mr Worm's GonePage: The Grinder</a>
      </td>

      <td>Blog entry on The Grinder.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://www.mooreds.com/weblog/archives/000111.html">Dan Moore!: The Grinder</a>
      </td>

      <td>Blog entry on The Grinder 3.</td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Commercials</title>

  <p>This section contains links to commercial products and services
  related to The Grinder. You should not assume any relationship other
  than those documented below between the listed individuals and
  companies and The Grinder project.

  If you have a product or service related to The Grinder and would
  like to add information to this page, please email details to <a
  href="ext:mail/grinder-use">grinder-use</a>.</p>

  <section id="perfmetrix">
    <title>Perfmetrix</title>

    <p>Perfmetrix is a global group of highly skilled and experienced
    system architects and performance experts ready to assist you with
    a comprehensive range of services to create or improve software
    applications that meet or exceed your business needs. We have presence
    in the United States, Europe, the Middle East, Africa and Latin America.
    </p>

    <p>Perfmetrix is led by Peter Zadrozny, who was the Chief Technologist
    of BEA Systems for Europe, Middle East and Africa, a role he had since
    he started the operations of WebLogic in Europe (prior to the BEA
    acquisition).
    </p>

    <p>Peter is the author of <a href="site:links/book">J2EE Performance Testing</a>
    (Expert Press, 2002), coauthor of "Professional J2EE Programming with
     BEA WebLogic Server" (WroxPress, 2000) and "Beginning EJB 3 Application
     Development" (Apress 2006). He is the founding editor of the WebLogic
     Developer's Journal, and a frequent speaker on technology issues around the
     world. Peter was also part of the team that created The Grinder.
    </p>


    <p>Peter Zadrozny, <a href="ext:perfmetrix">Perfmetrix</a></p>

  </section>

  <section id="anser-e">
    <title>Anser Enterprise</title>

    <p>One of my consulting services is helping performance analysts
    to set up company-internal blogs on their performance activities
    to help them communicate better with their developers and
    management. As part of my consulting service I can offer usage and
    customization tips on The Grinder and a separate data
    visualization tool to show Grinder test results on their company's
    intranet. Much of this is in the area of test automation and
    mining test results.</p>

    <p>Here's a <a href="ext:anser-e/run6">link</a> which provides
    several example web pages on communicating WebLogic 8.1/Grinder
    testing results. It requires downloading the Java 1.5 plug-in for
    charting Grinder test results.</p>

    <p>Todd Nichols, <a href="ext:anser-e">Anser Enterprise</a></p>
  </section>

  <section id="testpros">
    <title>TestPros</title>

    <p>TestPros provides load testing and performance tuning services
    using Grinder. We can provide our services in one or a combination
    of three ways - remotely via our Internet server farm, at our test
    labs, or at our customer's location.</p>

    <p>For more information:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>1-877-783-7855</li>
      <li><a href="ext:testpros/mail">info@TestPros.com</a></li>
      <li><a href="ext:testpros">www.TestPros.com</a></li>
    </ul>
  </section>

  <section id="swtest-discuss">
    <title>swtest-discuss</title>

    <p>I run a mailing list for software testers called <a
    href="ext:swtest-discuss">swtest-discuss</a>. There are a few
    people there (including me) who are interested in talking about
    how people do testing for open source projects. I haven't yet
    found a community of open source testers that cuts across multiple
    tools/applications.</p>

    <p>If you're interested in sharing your experiences in testing
    open source software, please consider joining swtest-discuss, at
    least long enough to see if there's any interest in having an
    on-going forum on this topic. If you do subscribe, please either
    send me a private email or introduce yourself to the list so we
    know you're there.</p>

    <p>Danny R. Faught, <a href="ext:tejasconsulting">Tejas Software
    Consulting</a></p>
  </section>

  <section id="book">
    <title>J2EE Performance Testing</title>

    <p>I'm pleased to announce the availability of <em><a
    href="ext:j2ee-performance-testing">J2EE Performance Testing with
    BEA WebLogic Server</a></em> by Peter Zadrozny, Philip Aston and
    Ted Osborne, originally published by Expert Press and now by
    APress.</p>

    <figure src="images/book-cover.jpg" alt="The Book"/>

    <p>This book uses The Grinder 2 throughout, and indeed was
    responsible for driving the development of many of The Grinder's
    features. The book shows how to performance test complete J2EE
    applications and how to explore key performance issues surrounding
    the most popular J2EE APIs. The performance tests are carried out
    using BEA WebLogic Server&#8482;, but are generally applicable to
    any J2EE application server.</p>

    <p>Most importantly, the book contains in-depth coverage of The
    Grinder 2 including a full user guide and case studies showing how
    to apply The Grinder to real world problems. The testing approach
    is equally applicable when using The Grinder 3.</p>

    <p>Following several requests, I've made the source code for the
    book available from <a href="ext:sourceforge/grinder">The Grinder
    SourceForge page</a>. This source is supplied unsupported and with
    no warranty.</p>

    <p>Philip Aston</p>

  </section>
</section>
</body>
</document>
