<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>Clojure</title>
</header>
<body>

  <p>The Grinder 3.6 and later optionally support <a
  href="ext:clojure">Clojure</a> as an alternative language for test
  scripts.</p>

  <section>
    <title>How to use Clojure</title>

    <p>Install Clojure and add the path to the installation's <code>clojure-x.x.x.jar</code>
    file to the start of the <code>CLASSPATH</code> you use for The Grinder agent processes.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Clojure scripting</title>

    <section>
      <title>Script structure</title>

      <p>Clojure scripts must conform to a few conventions in order to work
      with The Grinder framework.</p>

      <ol>
        <li>
          <strong>Scripts must return a function that creates test runner functions</strong>

          <p>When a worker process starts, it runs the test script
          once. The test script should return a factory function that
          creates and returns a <em>test runner function</em>.</p>

	  <p>Each worker thread calls the factory function to create a
	  test runner function. Worker threads perform a number of
	  <em>runs</em> of the test script, as configured by the
	  property <code>grinder.runs</code>. For each run, the worker
	  thread calls its test runner function; thus the test
	  runner function can be thought of as the definition of a
	  run.</p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <strong>The test script can access services through the
          <code>grinder</code> object</strong>

          <p>The engine makes an object called <code>grinder</code>
          available for the script to import. It can also be imported
          by any modules that the script calls. This is an instance of
          the <a
          href="site:api/ScriptContext">Grinder.ScriptContext</a>
          class and provides access to context information (such as
          the worker thread ID) and services (such as logging and
          statistics).</p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <strong>The script file name must end in <code>.clj</code></strong>

          <p>The file name suffix is used to identify Clojure
          scripts.</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Canonical test script structure</title>

      <p>This is an example of a script that conforms to the rules
      above. It doesn't do very much - every run will log <em>Hello
      World</em> to the output log.</p>

<source class="clojure">
;; helloworld.clj
(let [grinder net.grinder.script.Grinder/grinder]

  ;; The script returns a factory function, called once by each worker
  ;; thread.
  (fn []

    ;; The factory function returns test runner function.
    (fn []	
      (do
        (.. grinder (getLogger) (info "Hello World"))))))
</source>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Recording an HTTP script</title>

      <p>You can use the TCPProxy to <a
      href="site:tcpproxy/clojure">record a Clojure script</a> from a
      browser session.</p>
    </section>

  </section>

</body>
</document>
