<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
    "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>The Console Service</title>
  </header>
  <body>

    <section id="console-service-intro">
      <title>Overview</title>
      
      <p>The console service provides an interface for automating The
      Grinder. It allows The Grinder to be controlled by a scheduler
      or a Continuous Integration framework such as Hudson/Jenkins;
      remote monitoring using a web browser; and creative
      possibilities such monitoring and influencing the test
      execution from a test script, perhaps by starting additional
      worker processes.</p>

      <p>You can use the console service to start and stop worker
      processes; change console options; distribute script files;
      start and stop recordings; and obtain aggregated test
      results.</p>

      <p>The first version of the console service was released as part
      of The Grinder 3.10, and provides REST web services. Future
      releases will provide other flavours of interface, such as a
      browser-based user interface, and event-driven publication of
      data.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="configuration">
      <title>Configuration</title>
      
      <p>The console hosts an HTTP server that runs the console
      service and the <a href="site:console/webui">web interface</a>.
      When the console is started, the server listens for HTTP
      requests on port 6373. For most users, the console service
      should work out of the box with no further configuration.</p>

      <p>If port 6373 is unavailable, an error message will be
      presented. This usually occurs because another program has
      claimed the port. Perhaps there two copies of the console have
      been started. You can change the HTTP port using the console
      options, and also set the HTTP host to your publicly accessible
      host name or IP address. In fact, unless you change the host
      name, the HTTP server will listen on localhost, and you'll only
      be able to connect to the console from local processes.</p>

      <p>You can check that the console service has started correctly
      by using your browser to access <a
      href="http://localhost:6373/version">http://localhost:6373/version</a>.
      If the service is running, the browser will display the version
      of The Grinder.</p>

      <section id="security">
        <title>Remote access and security considerations</title>
        <warning>
          You are responsible for your system's security.
        </warning>
        <p>For convenience, the default configuration listens on all
        interfaces. You can replace <em>localhost</em> in the URL with
        an externally accessible host name or IP address, and access
        the console service or the web interface from another
        computer on the network.</p>

        <p> Remote control is part of the rationale for both the
        console service and the web interface, but the requirement for
        remote access is more general. The console process must be
        exernally accessible so that it can be contacted by agent and
        worker processes running on other machines.</p>

        <p>However, remote access opens up the possibility of
        accidental or mallicious misuse by other networked computers.
        It is a particularly bad idea to open any port of any of The
        Grinder's processes to the Internet. The Grinder code is not
        written nor tested to withstand mallicious attacks, as
        required for Internet facing software such as web servers. An
        attacker might potentially find a way to use The Grinder as a
        vector. Neither the console service nor the web interface
        require a user to authenticate. The communication is not
        encrypted. At the very least, an attacker could easily disrupt
        your testing. At worst, they might be able to gain full
        control over your computers and network. You should configure
        your operating systems, network components, and firewalls to
        restrict access appropriately.</p>
      </section>

      <section id="headless">
	<title>Running without a GUI window</title>

	<p>If you don't use the classic <a href="site:console/ui">user
	interface</a>, you can start the console in in a terminal mode
	by passing the <code>-headless</code> option as follows.</p>
    
	<source class="text">
	  java -classpath lib/grinder.jar net.grinder.Console -headless
	</source>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="rest">
      <title>The REST interface</title>

      <p>The REST interface accepts HTTP <code>GET</code>,
      <code>POST</code>, and <code>PUT</code> requests.  The request's
      <code>Accept</code> header is used to select the formatting of
      the response.</p>
   

      <table>

	<tr>
	  <th>Accept header</th>
	  <th>Response body format</th>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>application/clojure</code></td>
          <td>Clojure data structure</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>application/json</code></td>
          <td>JSON</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>application/x-yaml</code></td>
          <td>YAML</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>text/html</code></td>
          <td>YAML wrapped in HTML</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><em>No accept header</em></td>
          <td>JSON</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><em>Other values</em></td>
          <td><em>406 Not Acceptable</em></td>
	</tr>
      </table>

      <p>The YAML in HTML support allows simple access to some of the
      services (those that use <code>GET</code>) from a web
      browser.</p>

      <p>Some of the <code>POST</code> and <code>PUT</code> requests
      require additional data to be supplied in the body of the
      request. The request's <code>Content-Type</code> header is used
      to determine whether the request body should be parsed as JSON,
      YAML, or a Clojure data structure.</p>

      <table>

	<tr>
	  <th>Content-Type header</th>
	  <th>Request body format</th>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>application/clojure</code><br/>
              <code>application/x-clojure</code></td>
          <td>Clojure map</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>application/json</code><br/>
              <code>application/x-json</code></td>
          <td>JSON object</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>application/yaml</code><br/>
          <code>application/x-yaml</code><br/>
	  <code>text/yaml</code><br/>
          <code>text/x-yaml</code></td>
          <td>YAML map</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><em>Other values</em></td>
          <td><em>Ignored</em></td>
	</tr>
      </table>
     
    <section id="rest-services">
      <title>Available services</title>

      <p>The following services are available.</p>

      <table>

	<tr>
	  <th>Method</th>
	  <th>URL</th>
	  <th>Description</th>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>POST</code></td>
	  <td><code>/agents/start-workers</code></td>
	  <td>Send a start signal to the agents to start worker processes.
	  Equivalent to the <a
	  href="site:console/ui/process-controls">start processes</a>
	  button.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>GET</code></td>
	  <td><code>/agents/status</code></td>
	  <td>Returns the status of the agent and worker processes.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>POST</code></td>
	  <td><code>/agents/stop</code></td>
	  <td>Terminates all agents and their worker processes. You
	  will usually want <code>/agents/stop-workers</code> instead.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>POST</code></td>
	  <td><code>/agents/stop-workers</code></td>
	  <td>Send a stop signal to connected worker processes.
	  Equivalent to the <a
	  href="site:console/ui/process-controls">reset processes</a>
	  button.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>POST</code></td>
	  <td><code>/files/distribute</code></td>
	  <td>Start the distribution of files to agents that have an
	  out of date cache. Distribution may take some time, so the
	  service will return immediately and the files will be
	  distributed in proceeds in the background.  The service
	  returns a map with an <code>:id</code> entry that can be
	  used to identify the particular distribution request. </td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>GET</code></td>
	  <td><code>/files/status</code></td>
	  <td>Returns whether the agent caches are stale (i.e. they
	  are out of date with respect to the console's central copy
	  of the files), and the status of the last file
	  distribution.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>GET</code></td>
	  <td><code>/properties</code></td>
	  <td>Return the current values of the console options.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>PUT</code></td>
	  <td><code>/properties</code></td>
	  <td>Set console options. The body of the request should be a
	  map of keys to new values; you can provide some or all of
	  the properties. A map of the keys and their new values will
	  be returned. You can find out the names of the keys by
	  issuing a GET to <code>/properties</code>.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>POST</code></td>
	  <td><code>/properties/save</code></td>
	  <td>Save the current console options in the preferences
	  file. The preferences file is called
	  <code>.grinder_console</code> and is stored in the home
	  directory of the user account that is used to run the
	  console.</td>
	</tr>


	<tr>
	  <td><code>GET</code></td>
	  <td><code>/recording/data</code></td>
	  <td>Return the current recorded data. Equivalent to the data
	  in the <a href="site:console/ui/results">results
	  tab</a>.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>GET</code></td>
	  <td><code>/recording/data-latest</code></td>
	  <td>Return the latest sample of recorded data. Equivalent to 
	  the data in the lower pane of the <a href="site:console/ui/results">results
	  tab</a>.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>POST</code></td>
	  <td><code>/recording/start</code></td>
	  <td>Start capturing data. An initial number of samples may
	  be ignored, depending on the configured console
	  options.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>POST</code></td>
	  <td><code>/recording/stop</code></td>
	  <td>Stop the data capture.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>GET</code></td>
	  <td><code>/recording/status</code></td>
	  <td>Return the current recording status.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>POST</code></td>
	  <td><code>/recording/reset</code></td>
	  <td>Discard all recorded data. After a reset, the model
	    loses all knowledge of Tests; this can be useful when swapping
	    between scripts. It makes sense to reset with
	    the worker processes stopped.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>POST</code></td>
	  <td><code>/recording/zero</code></td>
	  <td>Reset the recorded data values to zero.</td>
	</tr>

	<tr>
	  <td><code>GET</code></td>
	  <td><code>/version</code></td>
	  <td>Returns the version of The Grinder.</td>
	</tr>

      </table>

    </section>

    </section>

    <section id="rest-example">
      <title>Example session</title>

      <p>Let's have a look at an example terminal session that
      exercises the REST interface. We'll use <a
      href="ext:curl">curl</a> as a client, but other HTTP clients
      will work will as well.</p>


	<note>A web cast of a similar example session is <a
	href="ext:youtube/grinder-console-service">available on YouTube</a>.
	</note>

      <section>
	<title>Starting up</title>
      
	<p>First, we start the console, specifying
	<code>-headless</code> because we're not going to be using the
	GUI.</p>

      <source class="text">
% java -classpath lib/grinder.jar net.grinder.Console -headless

2012-05-30 18:33:30,472 INFO  console: The Grinder 3.10-SNAPSHOT
2012-05-30 18:33:30,505 INFO  org.eclipse.jetty.server.Server: jetty-7.6.1.v20120215
2012-05-30 18:33:30,538 INFO  org.eclipse.jetty.server.AbstractConnector: 
 Started SelectChannelConnector@:6373
</source>

        <p>You can see the console service is listening on port 6373,
        as expected.  Now open another terminal window, and check the
        lights are on.</p>

	<source class="text">
% curl http://localhost:6373/version

The Grinder 3.10-SNAPSHOT
</source>

        <p>The console service has responded with the appropriate
        version string, as expected.</p>

	<p>Next let's ask for the current
        console options.</p>

	<source class="text">
% curl http://localhost:6373/properties

{"httpPort":6373,"significantFigures":3,"collectSampleCount":0,
"externalEditorCommand":"","consolePort":6372,"startWithUnsavedBuffersAsk":true,
"scanDistributionFilesPeriod":6000,"resetConsoleWithProcesses":false
"sampleInterval":3100,"resetConsoleWithProcessesAsk":true,
"frameBounds":[373,168,1068,711],"httpHost":"","externalEditorArguments":"",
"ignoreSampleCount":0,"consoleHost":"","distributeOnStartAsk":false,
"propertiesNotSetAsk":true,"distributionDirectory":"/tmp/grinder-3.9.1/foo",
"propertiesFile":"/tmp/grinder-3.9.1/foo/grinder.properties",
"distributionFileFilterExpression":
"^CVS/$|^\\.svn/$|^.*~$|^(out_|error_|data_)\\w+-\\d+\\.log\\d*$",
"saveTotalsWithResults":false,"stopProcessesAsk":true,"lookAndFeel":null}
</source>

        <p>The console options are returned in the response body as a
        JSON object containing key/value pairs. This format is easily
        to parse with a scripting language, or JavaScript in a
        browser.</p>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Setting the properties</title>

        <p>Some of the console options are only relevant to the GUI,
        but others also affect the console service. The following
        command changes the distribution directory to the examples
        directory in our distribution, and selects the
        <code>grinder.properties</code> file.</p>

	<source class="text">
% curl -H "Content-Type: application/json" -X PUT http://localhost:6373/properties
    -d '{"distributionDirectory":"examples", "propertiesFile":"grinder.properties"}'

{"propertiesFile":"grinder.properties","distributionDirectory":"examples"}
</source>

        <p>The properties that were changed are returned in the
        response body.</p>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Connecting an agent</title>

        <p>In a third terminal window, let's start an agent. We'll be
        distributing files to the agent which it will cache in its
        working directory, so we'll do so in a temporary
        directory.</p>

	<source class="text">
% cd /tmp
% java -classpath ${GRINDER_HOME}/lib/grinder.jar net.grinder.Grinder

2012-05-30 18:54:30,674 INFO  agent: The Grinder 3.10-SNAPSHOT
2012-05-30 18:54:30,737 INFO  agent: connected to console at localhost/127.0.0.1:6372
2012-05-30 18:54:30,737 INFO  agent: waiting for console signal
</source>

        <p>The agent has connected to the console. We could start up
        other agents, perhaps on other machines; we'd just need to add
        <code>-Dgrinder.console.Host=console-machine</code> before
        <code>net.grinder.Grinder</code>.</p>

        <p>We can confirm that the console knows about the agent.</p>

	<source class="text">
% curl http://localhost:6373/agents/status

[{"id":"paston02:968414967|1338400470671|425013298:0","name":"paston02","number":-1,
"state":"RUNNING","workers":[]}]
</source>

        <p>The agent is running, and it has not yet started any worker
        processes. Now we'll distribute the scripts to the agent.</p>


	<source class="text">
% curl -X POST http://localhost:6373/files/distribute

{"id":1,"state":"started","files":[]}
</source>

        <p>File distribution is asynchronous - the result indicates
        that the distribution request has been queued, and allocated
        id 1. We can find out where it's got to by querying the
        status.</p>

	<source class="text">
% curl http://localhost:6373/files/status

{"stale":false,"last-distribution":{"per-cent-complete":100,"id":1,"state":"finished",
"files":["cookies.py","digestauthentication.py","ejb.py","jdbc.py","httpg2.py","console.py",
"slowClient.py","httpunit.py","sequence.py","jmssender.py","grinder.properties","sync.py",
"amazon.py","helloworldfunctions.py","form.py","xml-rpc.py","parallel.py","jaxrpc.py",
"scenario.py","threadrampup.py","statistics.py","jmsreceiver.py","helloworld.py",
"helloworld.clj","proportion.py","fba.py","scriptlifecycle.py","email.py","http.py"]}}
</source>

	<p>This tells us that the agent caches are no longer stale,
	and the distribution 1 completed, sending the list of files to
	the agents.</p>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Starting the workers</title>

	<p>We're going to have The Grinder start some worker processes
	and run the <a
	href="site:script-gallery/helloworld.py">helloworld.py</a>
	script, which is one of the files we've just sent.</p>

        <p>We previously set the console option
        <em>propertiesFile</em> to a properties file in the
        distributed files (we chose
        <code>grinder.properties</code>). Setting this option causes
        the agent to first look for any script file in its
        distribution cache, falling back to its working directory if
        the file isn't found. We can override the values in the
        distributed <code>grinder.properties</code> file in properties
        sent with the start command.</p>

	<note>Distributing the files to the agents is optional. If you
	do so, then be sure to set <em>propertiesFile</em> to a valid
	properties file in the distribution. Otherwise, the agent will
	resolve the script file name relative to its working
	directory, ignoring the files in the distribution cache. If
	you don't distribute the files you'll have to make sure the
	agent can find the script through some other means, such as a
	file system share.

	<br/> <br/>

	Properties supplied with the start command override those
	specified with <em>propertiesFile</em>, which in turn override
	those specified as system properties on the agent or worker
	process command lines, which in turn override those found in a
	<code>grinder.properties</code> file in the agent's working
	directory.
	</note>

	<p>The following starts two worker processes, to perform three
	runs of <em>helloworld.py</em>, using five worker threads
	each.</p>

	<source class="text">
% curl -H "Content-Type: application/json" -X POST http://localhost:6373/agents/start-workers -d '{"grinder.processes" : "2", "grinder.threads" : "5", "grinder.runs" : "3",  "grinder.script" : "helloworld.py" }'

success
</source>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Obtaining the results</title>

	<p>Let's stop the recording. Until we do this, the TPS will be
	calculated over an increasing duration, and steadily
	fall. When doing real tests, it's more common to set
	<code>grinder.runs</code> to <code>0</code> so that the
	workers don't stop until instructed to do so, and to record a
	period of data before they are stopped.</p>

	<source class="text">
% curl -X POST http://localhost:6373/recording/stop

{"state":"Stopped","description":"Collection stopped"}
</source>

        <p>We can now retrieve the recording data.</p>

	<source class="text">
% curl http://localhost:6373/recording/data

{"status":{"state":"Stopped","description":"Collection stopped"},
"columns":["Tests","Errors","Mean Test Time (ms)","Test Time Standard Deviation (ms)","TPS","Peak TPS"],
"tests":[{"test":1,"description":"Log method","statistics":[30,0,0.2,0.4,9.674298613350532,
9.67741935483871]}],
"totals":[30,0,0.2,0.4,9.674298613350532,9.67741935483871]}
</source>

        <p>There were 30 executions of Test 1 as expected (2 worker
        processes x 5 worker threads x 3 runs), with an average
        execution time of 0.2 ms.</p>
        
        
	<source class="text">
% curl http://localhost:6373/recording/data-latest

{"status":{"state":"Stopped","description":"Collection stopped"},
"columns":["Tests","Errors","Mean Test Time (ms)","Test Time Standard Deviation (ms)","TPS","Peak TPS"],
"tests":[{"test":1,"description":"Log method","statistics":[30,0,0.2,0.4,9.674298613350532,
9.67741935483871]}],
"totals":[30,0,0.2,0.4,9.674298613350532,9.67741935483871]}
</source>

        <p>Adding the -latest will retrieve the latest sample 
        data available. This is most useful to get near real time 
        data a currently executing test.<br/>  Again, there were 
        30 executions of Test 1 as expected (2 worker processes x
         5 worker threads x 3 runs), with an average execution time of 0.2 ms.</p>
        

      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Conclusion</title>

	<p>I hope you've enjoyed this quick tour of the console
	service. Start the console and an agent yourself, and have a
	play.</p>

	<note><strong>Tips</strong>
	<br/>
        If a call to a service results in <em>Resource not
        found</em>, check you've used the appropriate HTTP method
        (GET, PUT, or POST).
	<br/>
	You might find it simpler to run the console GUI
	(don't add <code>-headless</code> to the command line). This
	will allow you to see the current console status at a glance.

	</note>

      </section>
      
    </section>
    
  </body>
</document>
