<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
<title>The Classic Console User Interface</title>
</header>
<body>

    <note>Eventually we expect to retire the classic user interface in
    favour of the <a href="site:console/webui">web console</a>.</note>

  <section id="starting">
    <title>Starting the console</title>

    <p>You can start the console on one of the test machines as follows.</p>
<source class="sh">
java net.grinder.Console
</source>

    <p>After a short delay, the main console window will appear.</p>

    <figure src="../images/console-screenshot-g3.png" width="778" height="551" alt="The Console"/>
  </section>

  <section id="process-controls">
    <title>Process controls</title>

    <p>The <em>Start processes</em>, <em>Reset processes</em>, and <em>Stop
    processes</em> menu items send signals to Grinder processes that are
    listening. (See the <a
    href="site:properties">properties</a>
    <code>grinder.useConsole</code>, <code>grinder.consoleHost</code>
    and <code>consolePort</code>.) <em>Start processes</em> and
    <em>Reset processes</em> are also tool bar buttons. </p>

    <figure src="../images/console-start-and-reset.png" width="258" height="97" alt="Start Processes and Reset Processes toolbar buttons"/>

    <p>These controls will be disabled if no agents are connected to the console.
    You can check whether any agents are connected on the
    <a href="#Processes+tab">Processes tab</a>.</p>

    <p>Worker processes that are controlled by the console can be in one of
    three states:</p>

    <ol>
      <li>Initiated (waiting for a console signal)</li>

      <li>Running (performing tests, reporting to console)</li>

      <li>Finished (waiting for a console signal)</li>
    </ol>

    <p>The <em>Start processes</em> control signals to worker
    processes that they should move into the running state. Processes
    that are already running will ignore this signal. Processes that are in
    the finished state exit; the agent process will then reread the
    properties file, and launch new worker processes in the running
    state.</p>

    <p>The <em>Reset processes</em> control signals all the worker
    processes to exit. The agent process will then reread the
    properties file and launch new worker processes.</p>

    <p>The <em>Stop processes</em> control signals all processes,
    including the agent processes, to exit. This is infrequently used, you
    usually want to use <em>Reset processes</em> instead.</p>

    <note>Each time the worker processes run, they generate a new
    set of logs. Logs from previous runs are "archived" by renaming
    them. The number of logs that are kept from previous runs can be
    controlled with <code> grinder.numberOfOldLogs</code>.</note>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Sample controls</title>

    <p>The sample controls determine how the console captures reports
    from the worker processes. It is important to understand that
    these only control the console behaviour. For example, they do not
    adjust the frequency at which the worker processes send reports
    (see <a
    href="site:properties"><code>grinder.reportToConsole.interval</code></a>
    for that). Additionally, the sample controls do not interact in
    any way with the process controls.</p>

    <figure src="../images/console-sample-controls.png" width="407" height="193" alt="Sample controls"/>

    <p>The slider controls the period at which the console will take a
    <em>sample</em>. This involves adding up all the reports received
    over that sample interval and calculating the TPS as (number of
    tests that occurred)/(interval length). It is also the period at
    which the console graphs and statistics are updated.</p>

    <p>By default, the console starts updating the display and calculating
    totals from the first non-zero sample period. A non-zero sample
    period is one in which an update from a worker process was
    received. You can adjust how many non-zero sample periods the console
    ignores before starting capture with the
    <em>ignore samples</em> text field.</p>

    <p>The third control allows you to adjust how many samples the
    console will collect before stopping capture.</p>

    <p>You can also manually start and stop the sampling with the
    <em>Capture statistics</em>/<em>Stop capture</em> control. Use the
    <em>Save statistics</em> control to save the current set of
    statistics to a file.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Graphs and Results tabs</title>

    <p>On the console there are two tabs which display information about The Grinder and its tests. These are detailed below:</p>

    <section>
      <title>Graphs</title>

      <p>Each graph displays the 25 most recent Tests Per Second (TPS)
      values for a particular test. A new value is added every console
      sample period. The y-axis is scaled so that the full height
      represents the peak TPS value received for the test since the
      display was last reset.</p>

      <p>The colours are based on the relative response time. Long
      response times are more red, short response times are more yellow.
      This acts as an eye-catcher, allowing expensive tests to be easily
      spotted.</p>

    </section>

    <section>

      <title>Results</title>

      <p>The Results tab shows the results from The Grinder instrumentation.</p>

      <table>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Test</strong></td>

          <td>The test number as specified in the test script, eg. tests[14000] will display as Test 14000.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Description</strong></td>

          <td>The test description as specified in the test script.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Successful Tests</strong></td>

          <td>The total number of iterations of the test that were successfully executed by The Grinder during the test run.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Errors</strong></td>

          <td>The total number of iterations of the test that failed to be fully executed by The Grinder during the test run.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Mean Time</strong></td>

          <td>The mean time taken to execute the test and receive the full response from the target server/application, in milliseconds.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Mean Time Standard Deviation</strong></td>

          <td>The mean standard deviation of the time taken to execute the test and receive the full response from the target
          server/application, in milliseconds.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>TPS</strong></td>

          <td>Transactions per second. The average number of iterations of the test that successfully ran in a one second interval.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Peak TPS</strong></td>

          <td>Peak Transactions per second. The maximum number of iterations of the test that successfully ran in a one second interval.</td>
        </tr>

      </table>

      <p>There is additional instrumentation provided by the HTTPPlugin.</p>

      <table>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Mean Response Length</strong></td>

          <td>The mean size of HTTP response from the target server/application in response to the executed test, in bytes.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Response Bytes per Second</strong></td>

          <td>The mean number of bytes per second received from the target server/application, in bytes per second. This gives an indication of the amount of
          bandwidth being consumed by the test. This does not take into account the amount of traffic being sent to the target server/application.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Response Errors</strong></td>

          <td>The total number of HTTP Response Error Codes (eg, 404, 500 etc) received during the test run.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Mean Time to Resolve Host</strong></td>

          <td>The mean time taken to resolve the ip address of the target server from the Fully Qualified
          Domain Name, via hosts file or DNS, in milliseconds. This is the time relative to the start of the test iteration.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Mean Time to Establish Connection</strong></td>

          <td>The mean time taken to establish a tcp connection to the target server/application, in milliseconds.
           This is the time relative to the start of the test iteration.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Mean Time to First Byte</strong></td>

          <td>The mean time taken to receive the first byte of response from the target server/application, in milliseconds.
           This is the time relative to the start of the test iteration.</td>
        </tr>

      </table>
    </section>

    </section>

    <section>

      <title>Processes tab</title>

      <p>This tab displays information about the Agents, their worker processes and associated threads.</p>

      <table>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Process</strong></td>

          <td>The name of the process. A parent process will take the hostname of the box on which it is running
          Its child processes take the name of the parent process and add a suffix of "-x" where x is an integer,
          eg. myserver-0.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>Type</strong></td>

          <td>The type of process, eg. Agent or Worker.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><strong>State</strong></td>

          <td>Information about the state of the process, eg. "Connected" for an agent process and "Running" and
           "Finished" for a Worker process.</td>
        </tr>
      </table>

    </section>

    <section>

      <title>Script tab</title>

      <p>This tab contains the console support for script editing and distribution.
         The distribution controls are also accessible through the <strong>Distribute</strong> menu.</p>

      <note>Script editing and distribution is optional. You don't have to use it, but then you must
         copy property files and scripts to each machine that runs an agent, or use a shared drive.</note>

      <p>To use the script distribution, follow these steps:</p>

      <ol>
       <li><a href="#setdirectory">Set the directory for the script distribution</a></li>
       <li><a href="#createscript">Create a script and a property file</a></li>
       <li><a href="#selectproperties">Select the properties file to use</a></li>
       <li><a href="#distributefiles">Distribute the changed files to the agents</a></li>
       <li><a href="#startworkers">Start the Worker processes</a></li>
      </ol>

      <section id="setdirectory">
       <title>Set the directory for the script distribution</title>

       <p>The file tree on the left hand side of Script tab is shows the a view
       of local files on the console machine. Use
       the <strong>Distribute/Set directory...</strong> menu option or the tool
       bar button to set the distribution directory to the place
       where you want to store your scripts. All of the files below the directory will be
       distributed to the worker processes, so don't set it to <em>/home</em> or <em>C:\</em>.
       </p>

       <p>If you are using The Grinder for the first time, you might like to set
       the distribution directory to the <code>examples</code> directory in
       The Grinder installation.</p>
      </section>

      <section id="createscript">
       <title>Create a script and a property file</title>

       <p>You can use the console to create, view, and edit script files in the
       distribution directory. The editor is rudimentary, but good enough for
       basic editing.</p>

       <p>If your script relies on other files (including Jython modules), copy
       them below the distribution directory.</p>

       <p>You can also edit files in the distribution directory with a text editor of your choice.
       For convenience, you can define an external editor in the console options
       (<strong>File/Options.../Script Editor</strong>), and launch it by right-clicking
       on a file in the file tree and selecting <strong>Open with external editor</strong>.</p>

       <p>Once you have your script ready, create a
       <a href="site:properties">properties</a> file.
       The file name extension should be <code>properties</code>, and unless you have many
       different properties files in the directory, the file is usually called
       <code>grinder.properties</code>. If your script is not called <code>grinder.py</code>,
       add a <code>grinder.script</code> property to your properties file:</p>
       <source class="text">grinder.script = myscript.py</source>

       <p>
       The properties sent from the console are combined with any set
       in a <code>grinder.properties</code> file in the agent's working directory
       or <a href="site:properties/commandline">set
       on the agent command line</a>. If a property is specified in several
       places, the order of precedence is</p>
       <ul>
       <li>Properties sent by the console<em>[most important]</em></li>
       <li>Properties set on the agent command line</li>
       <li>Properties in the agent's local <code>grinder.properties</code> file <em>[least important]</em></li>
       </ul>

       <note>If your agents are running remotely to the
       console, you will need to set the <code>grinder.consoleHost</code> property
       (and <code>grinder.consolePort</code> if the console isn't using the
       default port) in the agent's command line or local
       <code>grinder.properties</code> so it can make the initial connection
       to the console.
       </note>
      </section>

      <section id="selectproperties">
       <title>Select the properties file to use</title>

       <p>Right-click on the properties file and chose <code>Select properties</code>.</p>

         <figure src="../images/console-select-properties.png" width="644" height="239" alt="Select properties"/>

       <p>The properties file and the script to which it refers will be indicated with a star.</p>
      </section>


      <section id="distributefiles">
       <title>Distribute the changed files to the agents</title>

       <p>Select the <strong>Distribute/Distribute files</strong> menu item, or click on the toolbar button.</p>

       <figure src="../images/console-distribute-files.png" width="220" height="41" alt="Distribute files toolbar button"/>

       <p>Each agent maintains its own local cache of the files below the distribution
       directory. When you select <strong>Distribute files</strong>,  any files that have changed
       will be sent to the agents. The distribution controls will only be enabled if one or more agents is
       connected to the console, and one or more files has been edited.</p>
      </section>

      <section id="startworkers">
       <title>Start the Worker processes</title>

       <p>Select <strong>Start processes</strong> as <a href="#process-controls">described above</a>.</p>
      </section>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Internationalisation help wanted</title>

    <p>If you are bilingual you might fancy <a
    href="site:contributing/translating">translating the console</a>
    into a language of your choice.</p>
  </section>

</body>
</document>

