<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>Coordination</title>
</header>
<body>

  <p>Most scripts are written so that their worker threads operate
  independently of each other. For web load generation, a worker
  thread corresponds to the actions of a single, independent user.
  Worker threads can generate unique data using methods such as <a
  href="site:api/ScriptContext/getProcessNumber">getProcessNumber()</a>
  and <a
  href="site:api/ScriptContext/getThreadNumber">getThreadNumber()</a>.
  Coordination of activity within a worker process can use standard
  Java or Jython synchronisation APIs.
  </p>

  <p>Occasionally a script needs to coordinate worker threads across
  multiple worker processes. The Grinder supports this requirement
  through a distributed synchronisation feature,
  <em>barriers</em>.</p>

  <section>
    <title>Barriers</title>

    <p>A <a href="site:api/Barrier">barrier</a> is a pre-arranged
    synchronisation point at which worker threads will wait for each
    other. There can be many synchronisation points; each uses a
    unique barrier name.
    </p>

    <p>Each worker thread that wants to participate in a
    synchronisation point should create a barrier with the given name
    using the <a href="site:ScriptContext/barrier">ScriptContext</a>. The
    worker thread can wait for all other threads that have created
    barriers with a particular name by calling <a
    href="site:api/Barrier/await">await</a>.
    </p>

    <p>Barriers are usually created in the
    <code>TestRunner.__init__</code> constructor to ensure every
    worker thread has created its barriers before any of the threads
    try to wait for the barrier. </p>

    <section>
      <title>Sample script</title>

<source class="jython">
 from net.grinder.script.Grinder import grinder

 class TestRunner:
   def __init__(self):
     # Each worker thread joins the barrier.
     self.phase1CompleteBarrier = grinder.barrier("Phase 1")

   def __call__(self):

     # ... Phase 1 actions.

     # Wait for all worker threads to reach this point before proceeding.
     self.phase1CompleteBarrier.await()

     # ... Further actions.
</source>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Barrier scope</title>

      <p>Distributed barriers that allow coordination across worker
      processes require that the worker processes are started with the
      console.
      </p>

      <p>Barriers are not shared across worker processes that are not
      started using the console, even if they are started by the same
      agent. In this case, each barrier will only provide coordination
      locally, between the worker threads of a worker process.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Barrier life cycle</title>

      <p>A worker thread can reuse a barrier by calling <a
      href="site:api/Barrier/await">await</a> again. The call will
      block until the other workers using barriers with the same name
      all call <code>await</code>.</p>

     <p>A worker thread can wait for a limited time by using one of
     the versions of <code>await</code> that allow a timeout to be
     specified. If the timeout elapses, the barrier instance will be
     cancelled and become invalid. Other worker threads will no longer
     wait for the cancelled barrier. A new barrier can be created if
     required.</p>

     <p>Worker threads can remove themselves from a synchronisation
     point by <a href="site:api/Barrier/cancel">cancelling</a> a
     barrier directly.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

</body>
</document>
