<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>Features of The Grinder 3</title>
</header>

<body>
  <p>Thanks to <strong>Edwin DeSouza</strong> for his help in
  compiling this feature list.<br/>Last updated: 4 October 2011</p>

  <section>
    <title>Capabilities of The Grinder</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Load Testing</td>

        <td>Load Testing determines if an application can support a
        specified load (for example, 500 concurrent users) with
        specified response times. Load Testing is used to create
        benchmarks.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Capacity Testing</td>

        <td>Capacity Testing determines the maximum load that an
        application can sustain before system failure.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Functional Testing</td>

        <td>Functional Testing proves the correct behaviour of an
        application.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Stress Testing</td>

        <td>Stress Testing is load testing over an extended period of
        time. Stress Testing determines if an application can meet
        specified goals for stability and reliability, under a
        specified load, for a specified time period.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Open Source</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>BSD style license</td>

        <td>The Grinder is distributed under a BSD style license.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Dependencies</td>

        <td>The Grinder depends on a number of other open source products
        including

        <ul>

        <li><a href="ext:jython">Jython</a></li>

        <li><a href="ext:innovation/httpclient">HTTPClient</a></li>

        <li><a href="ext:jedit-syntax">JEdit Syntax</a></li>

        <li><a href="ext:xmlbeans">Apache XMLBeans</a></li>

        <li><a href="ext:picocontainer">PicoContainer</a></li>

        <li><a href="ext:clojure">Clojure</a></li>

        </ul>

        </td>
      </tr>

    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Standards</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>100% Pure Java</td>

        <td>The Grinder works on any hardware platform and any
        operating system that supports J2SE 1.4 and above.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Web Browsers</td>

        <td>The Grinder can simulate web browsers and other devices
        that use HTTP, and HTTPS.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Web Services</td>

        <td>The Grinder can be used to test Web Service interfaces
        using protocols such as SOAP and XML-RPC.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Database</td>

        <td>The Grinder can be used to test databases using JDBC.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Middleware</td>

        <td>The Grinder can be used to test RPC and MOM based systems
        using protocols such as IIOP, RMI/IIOP, RMI/JRMP, and
        JMS.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Other Internet protocols</td>

        <td>The Grinder can be used to test systems that utilise other
        protocols such as POP3, SMTP, FTP, and LDAP.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Grinder Architecture</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Goal</td>

        <td>Minimize system resource requirements while maximizing the
        number of test contexts ("virtual users").</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Multi-threaded, multi-process</td>

        <td>Each test context runs in its own thread. The threads can
        be split over many processes depending on the requirements of
        the test and the capabilities of the load injection
        machine.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Distributed</td>

        <td>The Grinder makes it easy to coordinate and monitor the
        activity of processes across a network of many load injection
        machines from a central console.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Scalable</td>

        <td>The Grinder typically can support several hundred HTTP
        test contexts per load injection machine. (The number varies
        depending on the type of test client). More load injection
        machines can be added to generate bigger loads.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Console</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Graphical Interface</td>

        <td>100% Java Swing user interface.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Process coordination</td>

        <td>Worker processes can be started, stopped and reset from
        one central console.
  </td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Process monitoring</td>

        <td>Dynamic display of current worker processes and
        threads.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Internationalised and Localised</td>

        <td>English, French, Spanish, and German translations are
        supplied. Users can add their own translations.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Script editing</td>

        <td>Central editing and management of test scripts.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Statistics, Reports, Charts</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Test monitoring</td>

        <td>Pre-defined charts for response time, test throughput.
        Display the number of invocations, test result (pass/fail),
        average, minimum and maximum values for response time and
        tests per second for each test.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Data collation</td>

        <td>Collates data from worker processes. Data can be saved for
        import into a spreadsheet or other analysis tool.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Instrument anything</td>

        <td>The Grinder records statistics about the number of times
        each test has been called and the response times achieved. Any
        part of the test script can be marked as a test.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Statistics engine</td>

        <td>Scripts can declare their own statistics and report
        against them. The values will appear in the console and the
        data logs. Composite statistics can be specified as
        expressions involving other statistics.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Script</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Record real users</td>

        <td>Scripts can be created by recording actions of a real user
        using the TCP Proxy. The script can then be customised by
        hand.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Powerful scripting in Python</td>

        <td>Simple to use but powerful, fully object-oriented
        scripting.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Multiple scenarios</td>

        <td>Arbitrary looping and branching allows the simulation of
        multiple scenarios. Simple scenarios can be composed into more
        complex scenarios. For example, you might allocate 10% of test
        contexts to a login scenario, 70% to searching, 10% to
        browsing, and 10% to buying; or you might have different
        workloads for specific times of a day.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Access to any Java API</td>

        <td>Test scripts can directly access any Java API.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Parameterization of input data</td>

        <td>Input data (e.g. URL parameters, form fields) can be
        dynamically generated. The source of the data can be anything
        including flat files, random generation, a database, or
        previously captured output.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Content Verification</td>

        <td>Scripts have full access to test results. In the future,
        The Grinder will include support for enhanced parsing of
        common results such as HTML pages.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Grinder Plug-ins</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>HTTP</td>

        <td>The Grinder has special support for HTTP that
        automatically handles cookie and connection management for
        test contexts.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Custom</td>

        <td>Users can write their own plug-ins to a documented
        interface; although this is rarely necessary due to the
        powerful scripting facilities.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>HTTP Plug-in</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>HTTP 1.0, HTTP 1.1</td>

        <td>Support for both HTTP 1.0 and HTTP 1.1 is provided.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>HTTPS</td>

        <td>The Grinder supports  HTTP over SSL.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Cookies</td>

        <td>Full support for Cookies is provided.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Multi-part forms</td>

        <td>The Grinder supports multi-part forms.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Connection throttling</td>

        <td>Low bandwidth client connections can be simulated.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>TCP Proxy</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>TCP proxy</td>

        <td>A TCP proxy utility is supplied that can be used to
        intercept system interaction at the protocol level. It is
        useful for recording scripts and as a debugging tool.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>HTTP Proxy</td>

        <td>The TCP proxy can be configured as an HTTP/HTTPS proxy for
        easy integration with web browsers.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>SSL Support</td>

        <td>The TCP proxy can simulate SSL sessions.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Filter-based architecture</td>

        <td>The TCP proxy has a pluggable filter architecture. Users
        can write their own filters.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Documentation</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>User Guide</td>

        <td><a
        href="site:getting-started">http://grinder.sourceforge.net/g3/getting-started.html</a></td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>FAQs</td>

        <td><a
        href="site:gfaq/contents">http://grinder.sourceforge.net/faq.html</a></td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Tutorial</td>

        <td><a
        href="site:tutorial">http://grinder.sourceforge.net/g3/tutorial-perks.html</a></td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Script Gallery</td>

        <td><a
        href="site:script-gallery">http://grinder.sourceforge.net/g3/script-gallery.html</a></td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Articles</td>

        <td><a
        href="site:links">http://grinder.sourceforge.net/links.html</a></td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>Commercial books</td>

        <td><em>Professional Java 2 Enterprise Edition with BEA
        WebLogic Server</em> <br/> <em><a href="site:links/book">J2EE
        Performance Testing</a></em></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Support</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>Mailing Lists</td>

        <td>
          <a
          href="site:mail/grinder-use">grinder-use@lists.sourceforge.net</a><br/>
          <a
          href="site:mail/grinder-development">grinder-development@lists.sourceforge.net</a><br/>
          <a
          href="site:mail/grinder-announce">grinder-announce@lists.sourceforge.net</a>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>

</body>
</document>
