<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>Getting started</title>
</header>

<body>
  <note>This section takes a top down approach to The Grinder. If you
  are happy figuring things out for yourself and want to get your
  hands dirty, you might like to read <a href="#howtostart">How do I
  start The Grinder?</a> and then jump to the <a
  href="site:script-gallery">Script Gallery</a>.</note>

  <section>
    <title>The Grinder processes</title>

    <p>The Grinder is a framework for running test scripts across a
    number of machines. The framework is comprised of three types of
    <em>process</em> (or program):
    <em><a href="site:processes/workers">worker processes</a></em>,
    <em><a href="site:processes/agents">agent processes</a></em>,
    and the <em> <a href="site:console/overview">console</a></em>.
    The responsibilities of each of the process types are:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <strong>Worker processes</strong>
        <ul>
          <li>Interprets test scripts and performs the tests.<br/> Each worker process can run many tests in parallel using a
          number of <em>worker threads</em>.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>

      <li>
        <strong>Agent processes</strong>
        <ul>
          <li>Long running process that starts and stops worker processes as required.</li>
          <li>Maintains a local cache of test scripts distributed from the console.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>

      <li>
        <strong>The Console</strong>
        <ul>
          <li>Coordinates the other processes.</li>
          <li>Hosts several types of user and machine interface.</li>
          <li>Collates and displays statistics.</li>
          <li>Provides script editing and distribution.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>

    <p>As The Grinder is written in Java, each of these processes is a
    Java Virtual Machine (JVM).</p>

    <figure src="../images/processes.png" width="600" height="507"
    alt="The Grinder processes"/>

    <p>For heavy duty testing, you start an agent process on each of
    several load injector machines. The worker processes they launch can be
    controlled and monitored using the console. There is little reason
    to run more than one agent on each load injector, but you can if
    you wish.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Tests and test scripts</title>

    <p>A <em>test</em> is a unit of work against which statistics are
    recorded. Tests are uniquely defined by
    a <em>test number</em> and also have a <em>description</em>.
    Users specify which tests to run using a <a
    href="site:scripts-intro">test script</a>.
    If you wish your scripts can report many different actions (e.g.
    different web page requests) against the same test, The Grinder
    will aggregate the results.</p>

    <p>The script is executed many times in a typical testing
    scenario. Each worker process has a number of worker threads, and
    each worker thread calls the script a number of times. A single
    execution of a test script is called a <em>run</em>.</p>

    <p>You can write scripts for use with the Grinder by hand. There are a
    number of examples of how to do this in the
    <a href="site:script-gallery">Script Gallery</a>. See the
    <a href="site:scripts/scripts-intro">Scripts</a> section for more details
    on how to create scripts.</p>

    <p>If you are creating a script to test a web site or web application, you
    can use the
    <a href="site:g3/tcpproxy/HTTPPluginTCPProxyFilter">
    TCPProxy</a> to record a browser session as a script.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Network communication</title>

    <p>Each worker process sets up a network connection to the
    console to report statistics. Each agent process sets up a
    connection to the console to receive commands, which it passes on
    to its worker processes. The console listens for both types of
    connection on a particular address and port. By default, the
    console listens on port <code>6372</code> on all local network
    interfaces of the machine running the console.</p>

    <p>If an agent process fails to connect to the console, or the
    <code>grinder.useConsole</code> property is <code>false</code>,
    the agent will continue independently without the console and
    automatically will start its worker processes. The worker
    processes will run to completion and not report to the
    console. This can be useful when you want to quickly try out a test
    script without bothering to start the console. </p>

    <note>To change the console addresses, set the
    <code>grinder.consoleHost</code> and
    <code>grinder.consolePort</code> properties in the <a
    href="site:properties"><code>grinder.properties</code></a>
    file before starting The Grinder agents. The values should match those specified
    in the console options dialog.</note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Output</title>

    <p>Each worker process writes logging information to a file called
    <code>host-n.log</code>, where <code> host</code> is the machine
    host name and <code>n</code> is the worker process number.</p>

    <p>Data about individual test invocations is written into a file called
    <code>host-n-data.log</code> that can be imported into a
    spreadsheet tool such as Microsoft Excel<sup>TM</sup> for further
    analysis. The data file is the only place where information about
    individual tests is recorded; the console displays only aggregate
    information.</p>

    <p>The final statistics summary (in the log file of each process)
    looks something like this:</p>

<source class="text">
Final statistics for this process:

              Successful
              Tests         Errors        Mean Test    Test Time
                                          Time (ms)    Standard
                                                       Deviation
                                                       (ms)

Test 0        25            0             255.52       22.52
Test 1        25            0             213.40       25.15
Test 2        25            0             156.80       20.81         "Image"
Test 3        25            0             90.48        14.41
Test 4        25            0             228.68       23.97         "Login page"
Test 5        25            0             86.12        12.53         "Security check"
Test 6        25            0             216.20       8.89
Test 7        25            0             73.20        12.83
Test 8        25            0             141.92       18.36
Test 9        25            0             104.68       19.86         "Logout page"

Totals        250           0             156.70       23.32
</source>

    <p>The console has a dynamic display of similar information
    collected from all the worker processes. Plug-ins and advanced test
    scripts can provide additional statistics; for example, the HTTP plug-in
    adds a statistic for the content length of the response body.</p>

    <p>Each test has one of two possible outcomes:</p>

    <ol>
      <li>Success. The number of <em>Successful Tests</em> for that
      test is incremented The time taken to perform the test is added
      to the <em>Total</em>.</li>

      <li>Error. The execution of a test raised an exception. The
      number of <em>Errors</em> for the test is incremented. The time taken
      is discarded.</li>
    </ol>

    <p>The <em>Total</em>, <em>Mean</em>, and <em>Standard Deviation</em>
    figures are calculated based only on successful tests.</p>
  </section>

  <section id="howtostart">
    <title>How do I start The Grinder?</title>

    <p>It's easy:</p>

    <ol>
      <li>Create a <a
      href="site:properties"><code>grinder.properties</code></a> file.
      This file specifies general control information (how the worker
      processes should contact the console, how many worker processes
      to use, ..), as well as the name of the test script that will
      be used to run the tests.<p/></li>

      <li>Set your <code>CLASSPATH</code> to include the
      <code>grinder.jar</code> file which can be found in the
      <code>lib</code> directory.<p/></li>

      <li>Start the <a href="site:console">console</a> on one of the test machines:
<source class="sh">
java net.grinder.Console
</source></li>

      <li>For each test machine, do steps 1. and 2. and start an agent
      process:
<source class="sh">
java net.grinder.Grinder
</source>
        <p>The agent will look for the <code>grinder.properties</code>
        file in the local directory. The test script is usually
        stored alongside the properties file. If you like, you can
        specify an explicit properties file as the first argument. For
        example:</p>

<source class="sh">
java net.grinder.Grinder myproperties
</source>
      </li>
    </ol>

    <p>The console does not read the <code>grinder.properties</code>
    file. It has its own options dialog (choose the
    <em>File/Options</em> menu option) which you should use to set the
    communication addresses and ports to match those in the
    <code>grinder.properties</code> files. The console <a
    href="site:console/ui/process-controls">process controls</a> can
    be used to trigger The Grinder test scenario. Each agent process
    then creates child worker processes to do the work.</p>

    <note>
    When you know a little more about the console, you can use it to
    <a href="site:console/ui/script-tab">edit and distribute
    properties files and scripts</a> instead of copying them to each
    agent machine.
    </note>

    <p>As the worker processes execute, they dynamically inform the
    console of the tests in the test script. If you start the console
    after the agent process, you should press the <em>Reset
    processes</em> button. This will cause the existing worker
    processes to exit and the agent process to start fresh worker
    processes which will update the console with the new test
    information.</p>

    <p>Included below are some sample scripts, for both Unix/Linux and
    Windows, for starting grinder agents, the console, and the
    <a href="site:tcpproxy">TCPProxy</a> for recording HTTP scripts.</p>

    <p><strong>Windows</strong></p>
    <ul>
     <li>setGrinderEnv.cmd
<source class="cmd">
set GRINDERPATH=<em>(full path to grinder installation directory)</em>
set GRINDERPROPERTIES=<em>(full path to grinder.properties)</em>\grinder.properties
set CLASSPATH=%GRINDERPATH%\lib\grinder.jar;%CLASSPATH%
set JAVA_HOME=<em>(full path to java installation directory)</em>
PATH=%JAVA_HOME%\bin;%PATH%
</source>
     </li>
     <li>startAgent.cmd
<source class="cmd">
call <em>(path to setGrinderEnv.cmd)</em>\setGrinderEnv.cmd
echo %CLASSPATH%
java -classpath %CLASSPATH% net.grinder.Grinder %GRINDERPROPERTIES%
</source>
     </li>
     <li>startConsole.cmd
<source class="cmd">
call <em>(path to setGrinderEnv.cmd)</em>\setGrinderEnv.cmd
java -classpath %CLASSPATH% net.grinder.Console
</source>
     </li>
     <li>startProxy.cmd
<source class="cmd">
call <em>(path to setGrinderEnv.cmd)</em>\setGrinderEnv.cmd
java -classpath %CLASSPATH% net.grinder.TCPProxy -console -http > grinder.py
</source>
     </li>
    </ul>

    <p><strong>Unix</strong></p>
     <ul>
      <li>setGrinderEnv.sh
<source class="sh">
#!/usr/bin/ksh
GRINDERPATH=<em>(full path to grinder installation directory)</em>
GRINDERPROPERTIES=<em>(full path to grinder.properties)</em>/grinder.properties
CLASSPATH=$GRINDERPATH/lib/grinder.jar:$CLASSPATH
JAVA_HOME=<em>(full path to java installation directory)</em>
PATH=$JAVA_HOME/bin:$PATH
export CLASSPATH PATH GRINDERPROPERTIES
</source>
      </li>
      <li>startAgent.sh
<source class="sh">
#!/usr/bin/ksh
. <em>(path to setGrinderEnv.sh)</em>/setGrinderEnv.sh
java -classpath $CLASSPATH net.grinder.Grinder $GRINDERPROPERTIES
</source>
      </li>
      <li>startConsole.sh
<source class="sh">
#!/usr/bin/ksh
. <em>(path to setGrinderEnv.sh)</em>/setGrinderEnv.sh
java -classpath $CLASSPATH net.grinder.Console
</source>
      </li>
      <li>startProxy.sh
<source class="sh">
#!/usr/bin/ksh
. <em>(path to setGrinderEnv.sh)</em>/setGrinderEnv.sh
java -classpath $CLASSPATH net.grinder.TCPProxy -console -http > grinder.py
</source>
      </li>
     </ul>
  </section>

</body>
</document>
