<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>The HTTP Plug-in</title>
</header>

<body>

  <section>
  <title>What's it for?</title>
  <p>The HTTPPlugin is a mature plug-in for testing HTTP services.
  It has a number of utilities useful for HTTP scripts as well as a
  tool, the  <a href="site:g3/tcpproxy/HTTPPluginTCPProxyFilter">TCPProxy</a>,
  which allows HTTP scripts to be automatically recorded. Recorded scripts
  are often customised, for example to simulate multiple users. This requires
  you to know a little about writing  <a
  href="site:g3/scripts/scripts-intro">scripts</a>.
  </p>

  <p>The HTTPPlugin is built into The Grinder and is automatically initialised
  whenever a script imports one
  of its classes. For example:</p>
  <source class="jython">
from net.grinder.plugin.http import HTTPRequest
</source>

  <p>The key class provided by the plug-in is
  <a href="site:api/HTTPRequest">HTTPRequest</a>.
  The best way to see how to use this class is to record a script with the
  TCPProxy.</p>

  <p>The plug-in wires itself into The Grinder script life cycle. It maintains a cache
  of connections and cookies for each worker thread which it resets at the beginning of each run.
  Each run performed by a worker thread simulates a browser session carried out by a user.
  Resetting a thread's cookies at the beginning of a run will cause server
  applications that use cookie-based tracking to create a new session.</p>

  <p>If your
  server application uses some other mechanism for session tracking
  (e.g. URL rewriting or hidden
  parameters), the script will have to capture and resend the appropriate token.
  The TCPProxy goes to some lengths to identify and record these tokens.
  </p>

  <p>If an <code>HTTPRequest</code> is instrumented with a
  <code>Test</code>, the plug-in contributes additional statistics,
  including the HTTP status code, the response body length, and
  additional connection timing information.  These statistics appear
  in the console and are recorded to the process data log.  If several
  <code>HTTPRequests</code> are instrumented within the same
  <code>Test</code> (e.g. they are called within an instrumented
  function), the status code of the last response is recorded.</p>
  </section>


  <section>
  <title>Controlling the HTTPPlugin</title>
  <p>The behaviour of the plug-in can be controlled from within scripts run by
  The Grinder through the use of the <a href="site:api/HTTPPluginControl">
  HTTPPluginControl</a> facade.</p>

  <section>
  <title>Levels of Control</title>
  <p>There are three levels of control of the behaviour of the HTTPPlugin that
  the HTTPPluginControl facade gives you access to:</p>
  <ol>
  <li><strong>Default Connection Behaviour</strong>
    <ul>
      <li><p>Method: <code>getConnectionDefaults</code></p></li>
      <li><p>Returns a <code>HTTPPluginConnection</code> that can be used to set
      the default behaviour of new connections.</p></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Thread Connection Behaviour</strong>
    <ul>
      <li><p>Method: <code>getThreadConnection</code></p></li>
      <li><p>Returns a <code>HTTPPluginConnection</code> for a particular URL.</p></li>
      <li><p>The resulting <code>HTTPPluginConnection</code> is valid for the current thread
      and the current run. It can be used to set specific authentication details,
      default headers, cookies, proxy servers, and so on for the current thread/run
      on a per-URL basis.</p></li>
      <li><p>This method will throw a <code>GrinderException</code> if not called from a worker thread.</p></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Thread HTTPClient Context Object Behaviour</strong>
    <ul>
      <li><p>Method: <code>getThreadHTTPClientContext</code></p></li>
      <li><p>Returns the HTTPClient context object for the calling worker thread. This is useful when
      calling HTTPClient methods directly, e.g. <code>CookieModule.listAllCookies(Object)</code>.</p></li>
      <li><p>This method will throw a <code>GrinderException</code> if not called from a worker thread.</p></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  </ol>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>Importing the HTTPPluginControl</title>
  <p>Place the following line at the top of your grinder script along with
  your other import statements</p>
<source class="jython">
from net.grinder.plugin.http import HTTPPluginControl
</source>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting HTTPClient Authorization Module</title>
    <p>The HTTPClient Authorization module is no longer enabled by default
    because it prevents raw authentication headers being sent through.
    The module also slows things down as HTTPClient must parse responses
    for challenges.</p>
    <p>Users who still wish to use the HTTPClient
    Authorization module can enable it using:</p>
<source class="jython">
control = HTTPPluginControl.getConnectionDefaults()
control.setUseAuthorizationModule(1)
</source>

     <p>The authentication details can be set using the <a
     href="site:api/AuthorizationInfo">AuthorizationInfo</a>
     API. HTTPClient maintains authentication information separately
     in each context, so the API must be called by each worker thread.
     See the <a href="site:script-gallery/digestauthentication">
     Digest Authentication sample</a> in the script gallery, as well
     as the example in the next section.</p>


  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting an HTTP proxy</title>

    <p>Should you need to specify an HTTP proxy to route requests through
    the following code can be used to specify the default proxy.</p>

<source class="jython">
control = HTTPPluginControl.getConnectionDefaults()
control.setProxyServer("localhost", 8001)
</source>

    <p>HTTP proxies can also be specified at the thread connection level. This
    is useful to set proxies on a per URL basis.</p>

<source class="jython">
proxyURL1 = HTTPPluginControl.getThreadConnection("http://<em>url1</em>")
proxyURL2 = HTTPPluginControl.getThreadConnection("http://<em>url2</em>")
proxyURL1.setProxyServer("localhost", 8001)
proxyURL2.setProxyServer("localhost", 8002)
</source>

    <p>If the HTTP proxy requires authentication, enable the HTTPClient Authorization Module, as described in the previous section. Having so, each worker thread can set up the appropriate authentication details using the <a href="site:api/AuthorizationInfo">AuthorizationInfo</a> API. For example:</p>

<source class="jython">
from net.grinder.plugin.http import HTTPRequest, HTTPPluginControl
from HTTPClient import AuthorizationInfo

defaults = HTTPPluginControl.getConnectionDefaults()
defaults.useAuthorizationModule = 1
defaults.setProxyServer("localhost", 3128)

class TestRunner:
  def __init__(self):
    AuthorizationInfo.addBasicAuthorization("localhost",
                                            8001,
                                            "My Proxy Realm",
                                            "joeuser",
                                            "pazzword",
                                            HTTPPluginControl.getThreadHTTPClientContext())

  def __call__(self):
    # ...
</source>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting HTTP Headers</title>
    <p>The HTTPlugin allows you to set the HTTP Headers sent with requests.
    The method takes the settings as header-name/value pairs</p>
<source class="jython">
control = HTTPPluginControl.getConnectionDefaults()
control.setDefaultHeaders(NVPair("<em>(header-name)</em>", "<em>(value)</em>"),))
</source>
    <p>Typical headers you might want to set here are <code>Accept</code> and its <code>Accept-*</code>
    relatives, <code>Connection</code>, <code>From</code>, <code>User-Agent</code>, etc.</p>
  <p> For example to disable persistent connections:</p>
<source class="jython">
control = HTTPPluginControl.getConnectionDefaults()
control.setDefaultHeaders(NVPair("Connection", "close"),))
</source>
   </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting Encoding</title>
    <p>Encoding for Content or for Transfer can be switched on and off using boolean flags</p>
<source class="jython">
control = HTTPPluginControl.getConnectionDefaults()
control.setUseContentEncoding(0)
control.setUseTransferEncoding(1)
</source>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting Redirect Behaviour</title>
    <p>Setting the HTTPPlugin behaviour with regards to following redirects can
    be switched on and off using boolean flags</p>
<source class="jython">
control = HTTPPluginControl.getConnectionDefaults()
control.setFollowRedirects(0)
</source>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting Local Address</title>
    <p>Should you be conducting your tests on a server with multiple network interfaces
    you can set the local IP address used by the HTTPPlugin for outbound connections.</p>
<source class="jython">
control = HTTPPluginControl.getConnectionDefaults()
control.setLocalAddress("<em>(local IP Address)</em>")
</source>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting Timeout Value</title>
    <p>The timeout value for used for creating connections and reading responses can be
    controlled via the HTTPPlugin. The time is specified in milliseconds.</p>
    <p>The following example sets a default timeout value of 30 seconds for all connections.</p>
<source class="jython">
control = HTTPPluginControl.getConnectionDefaults()
control.setTimeout(30000)
</source>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting Cookie Behaviour</title>
    <p>Setting the HTTPPlugin behaviour with regards to whether cookies are used or not can
    be switched on and off using boolean flags</p>
<source class="jython">
control = HTTPPluginControl.getConnectionDefaults()
control.setUseCookies(0)
</source>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Automatic decompression of gzipped responses</title>

    <p>For load testing, its often not practical to uncompress the response.
It's simply too expensive in CPU terms to do all that decompression in the
client worker process. This doesn't mean you can't test a server that compresses
its responses, just that you can't parse the responses in the script.</p>

   <p>On the other hand, there are times you may want to do this. The Grinder
supports decompression which it inherits from the
<code>HTTPClient</code> library, you just need to enable it. If your server
encrypts the content and sets a <code>Content-Encoding</code> header that starts
with one of { <code>gzip</code>, <code>deflate</code>, <code>compress</code>,
<code>identity</code> }, you can automatically decrypt the responses by adding
the following lines to the beginning of your script:</p>

<source class="jython">
from net.grinder.plugin.http import HTTPPluginControl
connectionDefaults = HTTPPluginControl.getConnectionDefaults()
connectionDefaults.useContentEncoding = 1
</source>

  <p>Similarly, if your server sets a <code>Transfer-Encoding</code> header
that starts with one of { <code>gzip</code>, <code>deflate</code>,
<code>compress</code>, <code>chunked</code>, <code>identity</code> }, you can
enable the HTTPClient Transfer Encoding Module with
<code>connectionDefaults.useTransferEncoding&nbsp;=&nbsp;1</code>.</p>

  <p>There is no support for automatically decrypting things based on their
<code>Content-Type</code> (as opposed to <code>Content-Encoding</code>,
<code>Transfer-Encoding</code>). Your browser doesn't do this, so neither should
The Grinder. If you really want to do this, you can use Java or Jython
decompression libraries from your script.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
	 <title>Streaming requests and response</title>

	 <p>The <a href="site:api/HTTPRequest">HTTPRequest</a>
	 class has support for sending request data from a stream. This allows an
	 arbitrarily large amount of data to be sent without requiring a corresponding
	 amount of memory. To do this, use these versions of the
    <a href="site:api/HTTPRequest/POSTStream">POST</a>,
    <a href="site:api/HTTPRequest/PUTStream">PUT</a>,
    <a href="site:api/HTTPRequest/OPTIONSStream">OPTIONS</a>,
    methods.
   </p>

   <p><code>HTTPRequest</code> allows the response body to be handled as a
   stream. Refer to the Javadoc for the
   <a href="site:api/HTTPRequest/setReadResponseBody">
   setReadResponseBody</a> method for more details.</p>

  </section>


  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using HTTPUtilities</title>

    <p>The HTTPPlugin provides an <code>HTTPUtilties</code> class:</p>

<source class="jython">net.grinder.plugin.http.HTTPUtilities</source>
  <p>This class has several methods which are useful for HTTP scripts.</p>

  <section>
     <title>Setting Basic Authorization</title>
     <p>The HTTPUtilities class can create an NVPair for an HTTP Basic Authorization header using the following method:</p>
<source class="jython">
httpUtilities = HTTPPluginControl.getHTTPUtilities()
httpUtilities.basicAuthorizationHeader('<em>username</em>', '<em>password</em>')
</source>

     <p>Include the header with each HTTPRequest that requires the authentication.</p>

<source class="jython">
request101.GET('/', (),
      ( httpUtilities.basicAuthorizationHeader('prelive', 'g3tout'), ))
</source>

  </section>
  <section>
     <title>Getting the Last Response</title>
    <p>The HTTPUtilities class can return the response for the last request made by the calling worker thread using the following method:</p>
<source class="jython">
httpUtilities = HTTPPluginControl.getHTTPUtilities()
httpUtilities.getLastResponse()
</source>
    <p>This returns the response, or <code>null</code> if the calling thread has not made any requests.</p>
    <p>This must be called from a worker thread, if not it throws a GrinderException.</p>
  </section>
  <section>
     <title>Getting a Token Value from a Location URI</title>
    <p>The HTTPUtilities class can return the value for a path parameter or query string name-value token with
        the given <code>tokenName</code> in a Location header from the last response. If there are multiple matches, the first value is returned.
    This utility can be invoked using the following method:</p>
<source class="jython">
httpUtilities = HTTPPluginControl.getHTTPUtilities()
httpUtilities.valueFromLocationURI(<em>tokenName</em>)
</source>
    <p> If there is no match, an empty string is returned rather than
        <code>null</code>. This makes scripts more robust (as they don't need to
        check the value before using it), but they lose the ability to distinguish
        between a missing token and an empty value.</p>
    <p>This must be called from a worker thread, if not it throws a GrinderException.</p>
  </section>
  <section>
     <title>Getting a Token Value from a URI in the Body of the Response </title>
    <p>The HTTPUtilities class can return the value for a path parameter or query string name-value token with
        the given <code>tokenName</code> in a URI in the body of the last
        response. If there are multiple matches, the first value is returned.
    This utility can be invoked using the following method:</p>
<source class="jython">
httpUtilities = HTTPPluginControl.getHTTPUtilities()
httpUtilities.valueFromBodyURI(<em>tokenName</em>)
</source>
    <p>This returns the first value if one is found, or <code>null</code>.</p>
    <p>This must be called from a worker thread, if not it throws a GrinderException.</p>
  </section>
  </section>


</body>
</document>
