<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>Jython</title>
</header>
<body>


  <section>
    <title>Scripts</title>

    <p>The core requirements for Jython scripts can be found in the <a
    href="site:scripts-intro/jython-scripts/">introduction</a>. </p>

    <section>
      <title>Importing modules</title>

      <p>Scripts can use code packaged in Jython <a
      href="site:python/modules>modules"> modules</a>. The Grinder
      adds both the directory containing the script and the <a
      href="site:scripts-intro/cwd">working directory</a> of the worker
      process (which may be the same) to the Python path, allowing
      modules to be imported from these locations.</p>

      <p>If you want to load modules from other locations, you should
      adjust the Python path. One way to do this is to set the <a
      href="site:jython/environment">JYTHONPATH</a> environment
      variable.</p>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="jython-installation">
    <title>The Jython distribution and installation</title>

    <p>The Grinder 3.11 includes Jython 2.5.3 and the Jython
    implementation of the standard Python library.</p>


    <section id="jython-cachedir">
    <title>Setting the Jython cache directory</title>

    <p>A Jython bug prevents the correct calculation of a default
    cache directory. If you don't have a Jython cache directory, wild
    card imports of Java packages (e.g.  <code> from java.util import
    *</code>) may not work, The Grinder will take a little longer to
    start, and ugly error messages will be displayed:
    </p>

    <source class="text">
28/09/08 17:57:11 (agent): worker paston01-0 started
*sys-package-mgr*: can't create package cache dir, '/home/performance/lib/jython.jar/cachedir/packages'
    </source>

    <p>You can specify the cache directory either by setting the
    <code>python.home</code> as described below (in which case the
    directory will that specified in the Python registry), or by
    setting the Java property <code>python.cachedir</code> in your <a
    href="site:properties">properties</a> file:
    </p>

    <source class="sh">
grinder.jvm.arguments = -Dpython.cachedir=/tmp/mycache
    </source>

    <p>or on the command line:</p>

    <source class="sh">
java -Dgrinder.jvm.arguments = -Dpython.cachedir=/tmp/mycache net.grinder.Grinder
    </source>

    <p>You can only set <code>grinder.jvm.arguments</code> once, so
    if you want to set both the cache directory and <code>python.home</code>
    either use the registry, or do this:</p>

    <source class="sh">
grinder.jvm.arguments = -Dpython.home=/opt/jython/jython2.5.3 -Dpython.cachedir=/tmp/mycache
    </source>

    </section>

    <section id="alternative-jython-versions">
      <title>Using an alternative Jython version.</title>

      <p>If you want use a different version of Jython, you should
      place it at the start of the classpath used to start the agent
      process.</p>

      <p>The Grinder is tested for compatibility with the many versions of Jython:
      <ul>
        <li>Jython 2.2.1</li>
        <li>Jython 2.5.0</li>
        <li>Jython 2.5.1</li>
        <li>Jython 2.5.2</li>
        <li>Jython 2.5.3</li>
        <li>Jython 2.5.4rc1</li>
        <li>Jython 2.7b1</li>
      </ul>

      Other versions may work, but versions earlier than 2.2.1 are no
      longer supported. Please report problems experienced with Jython
      2.2.1 or later, including versions not in the above list, to the
      <a href="site:mail/grinder-use">grinder-use</a> mailing
      list.</p>

      <p>If you don't use its standalone option, the Jython installer
      will create a new directory containing the Jython jar file, the
      library modules, examples, and documentation. To use the
      standard library modules, you need to tell The Grinder the
      location of this directory. You can do this either by adding the
      following to your <a href="site:properties">properties</a>
      file:</p>

      <source class="sh">
grinder.jvm.arguments = -Dpython.home=/opt/jython/jython2.5.3
      </source>

      <p>or on the agent command line:</p>

      <source class="sh">
java -Dgrinder.jvm.arguments=-Dpython.home=/opt/jython/jython2.5.3 net.grinder.Grinder
      </source>

      <p>In both cases, change <code>/opt/jython/jython2.5.3</code> to
      the directory in which you installed Jython. You must install
      Jython on all of the agent machines. If the version of Jython is
      different to that included with The Grinder (2.5.3), you should
      also add the installation's <code>jython.jar</code> to the start
      of the <code>CLASSPATH</code> used to launch the agent.</p>

      <p>Jython picks up user and site preferences from several
      sources (see <a
      href="ext:jython/registry">http://www.jython.org/docs/registry.html</a>).
      A side effect of setting <code>python.home</code> is that the
      installed registry file will be used.</p>
      </section>
  </section>

</body>
</document>
