<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>

<header>
    <title>Logging</title>
</header>

<body>

<section>

<title>Introduction</title>

<p> The Grinder 3.7 replaced a previous custom logging framework with
<a href="ext:logback">Logback</a>. Scripts now use a standard logging
API (<a href="ext:slf4j">SLF4J</a>), and Logback can be configured to
alter the output format, manage archiving of log files, and direct log
streams to alternative locations.</p>

</section>

<section>
<title>Changing the Logback configuration</title>

<p>The Grinder uses two Logback configuration files:</p>

<ul>

<li><code>logback.xml</code> - Used by all processes. Logs to the
terminal (<code>stdout</code>, <code>stderr</code>).</li>

<li><code>logback-worker.xml</code> - Used by worker processes.
Configures logging to the log file and the data log file.</li>

</ul>

<p>Both configuration files are located in the
<code>grinder-core.jar</code> file. Refer to the <a
href="ext:logback/manual">Logback manual</a> for full details of the
configuration file settings.</p>

<p>Let's change the archive settings for the output log to keep more
than one archive file. First, extract the configuration file.</p>

<source class="sh">
cd lib
jar xf grinder-core-3.7.jar logback-worker.xml
</source>

<p>Open the <code>logback-worker.xml</code> file in a text editor and
locate the <code>log-file</code> appender. To keep five archive files,
simply change the <code>maxIndex</code> setting to<code>5</code> so it
matches the following:</p>

<source class="xml"><![CDATA[

  <appender name="log-file"
    class="ch.qos.logback.core.rolling.RollingFileAppender">
    <file>${PREFIX}.log</file>

    <encoder>
      <pattern>%d %-5level %logger{0} %marker: %message%n</pattern>
    </encoder>

    <rollingPolicy class="ch.qos.logback.core.rolling.FixedWindowRollingPolicy">
      <fileNamePattern>${PREFIX}.log%i</fileNamePattern>
      <minIndex>1</minIndex>
      <maxIndex>5</maxIndex>
    </rollingPolicy>

    <triggeringPolicy class="net.grinder.util.logback.RollOnStartUp" />

  </appender>
]]>
</source>

<p>Save the file under the same name
(<code>logback-worker.xml</code>). To use the modified configuration,
add the file's directory to the <code>CLASSPATH</code> used to start
The Grinder. We extracted the file into the <code>lib</code>
directory, so we could start the agent process with something like the
following:
</p>

<source class="sh">
cd $GRINDER_HOME
java -classpath lib:lib/grinder.jar net.grinder.Grinder 
</source>

</section>

<section>
<title>Logging data to a database</title>

<p>The <code>logback-worker.xml</code> file configures two Logback
loggers: <code>worker</code> for the main log file, and
<code>data</code> for the data log file. Let's change the
configuration to send test data to a database. To do this, we'll
configure a new appender and add it to the data logger. Logback's
database appender supports several databases; here's a suitable
configuration for an Oracle database.
</p>

<source class="xml"><![CDATA[
  <appender name="data-db" class="ch.qos.logback.classic.db.DBAppender">
    <connectionSource class="ch.qos.logback.core.db.DriverManagerConnectionSource">
      <driverClass>oracle.jdbc.OracleDriver</driverClass>
      <url>jdbc:oracle:thin:@localhost:1521:XE</url>
      <user>grinder</user>
      <password>grinder</password>
    </connectionSource>
  </appender>

  <logger name="data" additivity="false">
    <appender-ref ref="data-file" />
    <appender-ref ref="data-db" />
  </logger>
]]>
</source>

<p>To expose any problems with the configuration, we'll also enable
the Logback debug output by changing the first line of the
configuration.</p>

<source class="xml"><![CDATA[
   <configuration debug="true">
]]>
</source>

<p>Before we can use the database appender, we need to set up the
appropriate database tables. To do this, create a suitable database
account (the configuration above uses an account called
<em>grinder</em>), download the Logback distribution, and locate and
execute the appropriate DDL
(<code>logback-classic/src/main/java/ch/qos/logback/classic/db/dialect/oracle.sql</code>
for Oracle).</p>

<p>To run the configuration, add the directory containing
<code>logback-worker.xml</code> to the <code>CLASSPATH</code>, along
with the appropriate database driver. For example:</p>

<source class="sh">
java -classpath /usr/lib/oracle/xe/app/oracle/product/10.2.0/server/jdbc/lib/ojdbc14.jar:lib:lib/grinder.jar  net.grinder.Grinder 
</source>

</section>

<section>
<title>Writing a custom appender for data logs</title>

<p>If you tried out the database configuration in the previous section
you may have noted the following drawbacks.</p>

<ul>

<li>It's not particularly fast. Maximum logging throughput is of the
order of a hundred log events per second, and this severely constrains
the rate at which a worker process can perform tests.</li>

<li>The log data is written as a string to a single
<code>formatted_message</code> column. This is not amenable to further
processing.</li>

</ul>

<p>To address these problems, you will have to write a custom database
appender, perhaps by modifying the standard Logback-supplied appender.
If you write such an appender, please consider making it generic and
contributing it back to The Grinder. The following sections contain
some implementation ideas.</p>

<section>
<title>Improving database logging performance</title>

<p>The most beneficial change from a performance perspective would be
to buffer the log events, and write many events to the database at
once. JDBC batching would further improve performance. I suspect that
this change alone would allow tens of thousands of events to be logged
per second.</p>

<p>The standard appender includes caller data (filename, class,
method, line) that is expensive to obtain and is of little use for The
Grinder data log. It also logs exception and property information.
These features can be removed.</p>

<p>To support the secondary exception and property tables, the
standard appender needs to obtain the primary key of the newly logged
event. Unfortunately this uses an appender level lock (unnecessarily,
it could have synchronised on the database connection instead), and
becomes a bottleneck when many worker threads are using the appender.
Since the exception and property tables are unnecessary, this
complexity can also be removed.</p>

</section>

<section>
<title>Customising data log output</title>

<p>The Grinder data logger generates <code>ILoggingEvent</code>s with
the formatted string set to a comma-separated string (formatted as in
the standard data log). It also supplies an instance of
<code>net.grinder.engine.process.DataLogArguments</code> as the first
and only argument. This can be accessed using
<code>ILoggingEvent.getArgumentArray()[0]</code>.</p>

<p>The <code>DataLogArguments</code> object provides all the
information you might need about a particular data log event,
including the thread and run numbers, the <code>Test</code>, and the
raw statistics. Refer to the
<code>net.grinder.engine.processs.ThreadDataLogger</code> source code
for an example of how to extract the appropriate statistics values
from the raw statistics. </p>

</section>



</section>
</body>
</document>
