<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>The Grinder 3 Properties File</title>
  </header>
  <body>
      <p>The Grinder worker and agent processes are controlled by
    setting properties in the <code>grinder.properties</code>
    file.</p>

    <p>All properties have default values. If you start The Grinder
    agent process without a <code>grinder.properties</code> file it
    will communicate with the console using default addresses, use one
    worker process, one thread, and make one run through the test
    script found in the file <code>grinder.py</code>. This is not much
    use, so read on...</p>

    <section>
      <title>Table of properties</title>

      <p>This table lists the properties understood by The Grinder
      engine.</p>

      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Property</th>
          <th>Description</th>
          <th>Default</th>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.processes</code>
          </td>

          <td>The number of worker processes the agent should start.</td>

          <td>1</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.threads</code>
          </td>

          <td>The number of worker threads that each worker process
          spawns.</td>

          <td>1</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.runs</code>
          </td>

          <td>The number of runs of the test script each thread
          performs. 0 means "run forever", and should be used when you
          are using the console to control your test runs.</td>

          <td>1</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.processIncrement</code>
          </td>

          <td>If set, the agent will <em>ramp up</em> the number of
          worker processes, starting the number specified every
          <code>grinder.processesIncrementInterval</code> milliseconds. The
          upper limit is set by <code>grinder.processes</code>.
          </td>

          <td>Start all worker processes together.</td>
  </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.processIncrementInterval</code>
          </td>

          <td>Used in conjunction with
          <code>grinder.processIncrement</code>, this property sets
          the interval in milliseconds at which the agent starts new
          worker processes.</td>

          <td>60000 ms</td>
  </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.initialProcesses</code>
          </td>

          <td>Used in conjunction with
          <code>grinder.processIncrement</code>, this property sets
          the initial number of worker processes to start.</td>

          <td>The value of <code>grinder.processIncrement</code>.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.duration</code>
          </td>

          <td>The maximum length of time in milliseconds that each
          worker process should run for. <code>grinder.duration</code>
          can be specified in conjunction with
          <code>grinder.runs</code>, in which case the worker
          processes will terminate if either the duration time or the
          number of runs is exceeded.</td>

          <td>Run forever.</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.script</code>
          </td>

          <td>The file name of the Jython <a
          href="site:scripts-intro">script</a> to run.</td>

          <td>grinder.py</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.jvm</code>
          </td>

          <td>Use an alternate JVM for worker processes. Defaults to
          <code>java</code> so you do not need to specify this if your
          <code>PATH</code> is sensible.</td>

          <td>java</td>
  </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.jvm.classpath</code>
          </td>

          <td>Use to adjust the classpath used for the worker process
          JVMs. Anything specified here will be prepended to the
          classpath used to start the Grinder processes. <p>Relative
          paths are evaluated based on the worker process <a
          href="site:scripts-intro/cwd">working directory</a>.
          Scripts distributed using the console can refer to libraries
          in the distribution directory by using relative
          paths in this property.</p></td>

          <td></td>
  </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.jvm.arguments</code>
          </td>

          <td>Additional arguments to worker process JVMs.</td>

          <td></td>
  </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.logDirectory</code>
          </td>

          <td>Directory to write log files to. Created if it doesn't
          already exist.</td>

          <td>The local directory.</td>
  </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.hostID</code>
          </td>

          <td>Override the "host" string used in log filenames and logs.</td>

          <td>The host name.</td>
  </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.consoleHost</code>
          </td>

          <td>The IP address or host name that the agent and worker processes
          use to contact the console.</td>

          <td>All the network interfaces of the local machine.</td>
  </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.consolePort</code>
          </td>

          <td>The IP port that the agent and
          worker processes use to contact the console.</td>

          <td>6372</td>
  </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.useConsole</code>
          </td>

          <td>Set to <code>false</code> to set the agent and worker
          processes not to use the console.</td>

          <td>true</td>
  </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.reportToConsole.interval</code>
          </td>

          <td>For advanced use only. The period at which each process
          sends updates to the console.</td>

          <td>500 ms</td>
  </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.initialSleepTime</code>
          </td>

          <td>The maximum time in milliseconds that each thread waits
          before starting. Unlike the sleep times specified in
          scripts, this is varied according to a flat random
          distribution. The actual sleep time will be a random value
          between 0 and the specified value. Affected by
          <code>grinder.sleepTimeFactor</code>, but not
          <code>grinder.sleepTimeVariation</code>.</td>

          <td>0 ms</td>
  </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.sleepTimeFactor</code>
          </td>

          <td> Apply a factor to all the sleep times you've specified,
          either through a property of in a script. Setting this to
          <code>0.1</code> would run the script ten times as fast.</td>

          <td>1</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.sleepTimeVariation</code>
          </td>

          <td>The Grinder varies the sleep times specified in scripts
          according to a Normal distribution. This property specifies
          a fractional range within which nearly all (99.75%) of the
          times will lie. E.g., if the sleep time is specified as 1000
          and the sleepTimeVariation is set to <code>0.1</code>, then
          99.75% of the actual sleep times will be between 900 and
          1100 milliseconds.</td>

          <td>0.2</td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.reportTimesToConsole</code>
          </td>

          <td>Set to <code>false</code> to disable reporting of <a
          href="site:faq/timing">timing information</a> to the
          console; other statistics are still reported.</td>

          <td>true</td>
    </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.debug.singleprocess</code>
          </td>

          <td>If set to <code>true</code>, the agent process spawns engines in
          threads rather than processes, using special class loaders to isolate
          the engines. This allows the engine to be easily run in a debugger.
          This is primarily a tool for debugging The Grinder engine, but it
          might also be useful to advanced users.
          <a href="site:grinderstone">GrinderStone</a> uses this property to
          allow interactive debugging.

          <p>If you want instrumentation to work, you must specify
          <code>-javaagent:path/grinder-dcr-agent-version.jar</code>
          on the command line. Here, <em>path</em> is the full path to
          the agent jar file that can be found in the <code>lib</code>
          directory, and <em>version</em> depends on the version of
          The Grinder.
          </p>
          </td>

          <td>false</td>
    </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <code>grinder.debug.singleprocess.sharedclasses</code>
          </td>

          <td>For advanced use only. Specifies a comma separated list of
          names of classes that should be shared between the worker engines when
          <code>grinder.debug.singleprocess</code> is <code>true</code>.
          Class names can end with a <code>*</code> wildcard. See
          <a href="site:sourceforge/bugs/shared-classes">bug 134</a> for more details.
          </td>

          <td></td>
    </tr>

      </table>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Specifying properties on the command line</title>

      <p>You can also specify these properties as Java system
      properties in the agent command line. For example, on UNIX
      systems the following command line can be used to generate log
      directories based on the current date.</p>

<source class="sh">
java -Dgrinder.logDirectory="log/$(date +%y%m%d)" net.grinder.Grinder
</source>

      <p>Property values set as Java system properties override values set in the
      <code>grinder.properties</code> file. Only properties with names that
      start "<code>grinder.</code>" are considered.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
