<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>Scripts</title>
</header>
<body>

  <p>This section describes The Grinder 3 scripting API. If you've
  used The Grinder 2 for HTTP testing and you're not a programmer, you
  might be a bit daunted. Don't worry, its just as easy to record and
  replay HTTP scripts with The&nbsp;Grinder&nbsp;3.</p>

  <section>
    <title>Jython and Python</title>

    <p>The default scripting engine is Jython - the Java
    implementation of Python. Python is powerful, popular and easy on
    the eye. If you've not seen any Python before, take a look at the
    <a href="site:script-gallery">script gallery</a> and Richard
    Perks' <a href="site:tutorial">tutorial</a> to get a taste of what
    its like. There are plenty of resources on the web, here are a few
    of them to get you started:</p>

    <ul>
      <li><a href="ext:jython">The Jython home page</a></li>
      <li><a href="ext:python">The Python language web site</a></li>
      <li><a href="ext:pythonpitfalls">Ten Python pitfalls</a></li>
    </ul>

    <p>I recommend the <a href="ext:amazon/jython-essentials">Jython
    Essentials</a> book; you can read the <a
    href="ext:oreilly/jython-essentials-c1">introductory chapter</a>
    for free.</p>

    <section>
      <title>Alternative languages</title>

      <p>The Grinder 3.6 and later support test scripts written in <a
      href="site:clojure">Clojure</a>.</p>

      <p>Ryan Gardner has written an add-on <a
      href="ext:grinder-groovy">script engine for Groovy</a>.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="jython-scripts">
    <title>Jython scripting</title>

    <section>
      <title>Script structure</title>

      <p>Jython scripts must conform to a few conventions in order to work
      with The Grinder framework. I'll lay the rules out in fairly dry
      terms before proceeding with an example. Don't worry if this
      makes no sense to you at first, the examples are much easier to
      comprehend.</p>

      <ol>
        <li>
          <strong>Scripts must define a class called
          <code>TestRunner</code></strong>

          <p>When a worker process starts up it runs the test script
          once. The test script must define a class called
          <code>TestRunner</code>. The Grinder engine then creates an
          instance of <code>TestRunner</code> for each worker thread.
          A thread's TestRunner instance can be used to store
          information specific to that thread.</p>

          <note>Although recommended, strictly <code>TestRunner</code>
          doesn't need to be a class. See the <a
          href="site:script-gallery/helloworldfunctions">Hello World
          with Functions</a> example.</note>
        </li>

        <li>
          <strong>The <code>TestRunner</code> instance must be
          callable</strong>

          <p>A Python object is callable if it defines a
          <code>__call__</code> method. Each worker thread performs a
          number of <em>runs</em> of the test script, as configured by
          the property <code>grinder.runs</code>. For each run, the
          worker thread calls its <code>TestRunner</code>; thus the
          <code>__call__</code> method can be thought of as the
          definition of a run.</p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <strong>The test script can access services through the
          <code>grinder</code> object</strong>

          <p>The engine makes an object called <code>grinder</code>
          available for the script to import. It can also be imported
          by any modules that the script calls. This is an instance of
          the <a
          href="site:api/ScriptContext">Grinder.ScriptContext</a>
          class and provides access to context information (such as
          the worker thread ID) and services (such as logging and
          statistics).</p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <strong>The script file name must end in <code>.py</code></strong>

          <p>The file name suffix is used to identify Jython
          scripts.</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Canonical test script structure</title>

      <p>This is an example of a script that conforms to the rules
      above. It doesn't do very much - every run will log <em>Hello
      World</em> to the worker process log.</p>

<source class="jython">
from net.grinder.script.Grinder import grinder

# An instance of this class is created for every thread.
class TestRunner:
    # This method is called for every run.
    def __call__(self):
        # Per thread scripting goes here.
        grinder.logger.info("Hello World")
</source>
    </section>
  <section>
      <title>Automatically generating scripts</title>
    <p>If you are creating a script for a website or web application, you can use the <a href="site:g3/tcpproxy/HTTPPluginTCPProxyFilter">TCPProxy</a> to generate an HTTPPlugin script
      suitable for use with The Grinder.</p>
  </section>
  </section>

  <section id="tests">
    <title>Tests</title>

    <p>Although our simple test script can be used with The Grinder
    framework and can easily be started in many times in many worker
    processes on many machines, it doesn't report any statistics. For
    this we need to create some tests. A <a
    href="site:api/Test">Test</a> has a unique test number and
    description. If you are using the <a
    href="site:console">console</a>, it will update automatically to
    display new <code>Test</code>s as they are created.</p>

    <p>Let's add a <code>Test</code> to our script.</p>

<source class="jython">
from net.grinder.script import Test
from net.grinder.script.Grinder import grinder

# Create a Test with a test number and a description.
test1 = Test(1, "Log method")

class TestRunner:
    def __call__(self):
        grinder.logger.info("Hello World")
</source>

    <p>Here we have created a single <code>Test</code> with the test
    number <em>1</em> and the description <em>Log method</em>. Note
    how we import the <code>grinder</code> object and the
    <code>Test</code> class in a similar manner to
    Java.</p>

    <p>Now the console knows about our <code>Test</code>, but we're
    still not using it to record anything. Let's record how long our
    <code>grinder.logger.info</code> method takes to execute.
    <code>Test.record</code> adds the appropriate instrumentation code
    to the byte code of method. The time taken and the number of calls
    will be recorded and reported to the console.</p>

<source class="jython">
from net.grinder.script import Test
from net.grinder.script.Grinder import grinder

test1 = Test(1, "Log method")

# Instrument the info() method with our Test.
test1.record(grinder.logger.info)

class TestRunner:
    def __call__(self):
        grinder.logger.info("Hello World")
</source>

    <p>This is a complete test script that works within The Grinder
    framework and reports results to the console.</p>

    <p>You're not restricted to instrument method calls. In fact, it's
    more common to instrument objects. Here's an example using The Grinder's
    <a href="site:g3/plugins/http-plugin">HTTP plug-in</a>.</p>

<source class="jython">
# A simple example using the HTTP plugin that shows the retrieval of a
# single page via HTTP.

from net.grinder.script import Test
from net.grinder.script.Grinder import grinder
from net.grinder.plugin.http import HTTPRequest

test1 = Test(1, "Request resource")
request1 = HTTPRequest()
test1.record(request1)

class TestRunner:
    def __call__(self):
        result = request1.GET("http://localhost:7001/")
</source>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Grinder script API</title>

    <p>With what you've seen already you have the full power of Jython
    at your finger tips. You can use practically <em>any</em> Java or
    Python code in your test scripts.</p>

    <p>The Grinder script API can be used to access services from The
    Grinder. The <a href="site:api/index">Javadoc</a> contains full
    information on all the packages, classes and interfaces that make
    up the core API, as well as additional packages added by the
    shipped plug-ins. This section provides overview information on
    various areas of the API. See also the <a
    href="site:g3/plugins/http-plugin">HTTP plugin
    documentation</a>.</p>

    <dl>
      <dt><strong>The <a
      href="site:api/script-package">net.grinder.script</a>
      package</strong></dt>

      <dd>
        <p>An instance of <a
        href="site:api/ScriptContext">Grinder.ScriptContext</a> called
        <code>grinder</code> is automatically available to all
        scripts. This object provides access to context information
        and acts a starting point for accessing other services. The
        instance can be explicitly imported from other Python modules
        as <code>net.grinder.script.Grinder.grinder</code>.</p>

        <p>We have described the use of the <a
        href="site:api/Test">Test</a> class <a
        href="#tests">above</a>.</p>

        <p>The <a href="site:api/Statistics">Statistics</a> interface
        allows scripts to query and modify <a
        href="site:g3/statistics">statistics</a>, provide custom
        statistics, and register additional views of standard and
        custom statistics.</p>

      </dd>

      <dt><strong>The <a
      href="site:api/common-package">net.grinder.common</a>
      package</strong></dt>

      <dd>
        <p>This package contains common interfaces and utility classes
        that are used throughout The Grinder and that are also useful
        to scripts.</p>
      </dd>

    </dl>
  </section>

  <section id="cwd">
    <title>Working directory</title>

    <p>When the script has been distributed using the console, the
    working directory (CWD) of the worker process will be the local
    agent's cache of the distributed files. This allows the script to
    conveniently refer to other distributed files using relative
    paths.</p>

    <p>Otherwise, the working directory of the worker process will be
    that of the agent process that started it.</p>

    <section>
      <title>Distributing Java code</title>

      <p>You can add Java <code>jar</code> or <code>.class</code>
      files to your console distribution directory and use the file
      distribution mechanism to push the code to the agent's cache.
      Use relative paths and the <code>grinder.jvm.classpath</code>
      property to add the files to the worker process
      <code>CLASSPATH</code>.
      </p>

      <p>For example, you might distribute the following files</p>
      <source class="text">     
grinder.properties
myscript.py
lib/myfile.jar
      </source>

      <p>where <code>grinder.properties</code> contains:</p>
      <source class="text">
grinder.script=myscript.py
grinder.jvm.classpath=lib/myfile.jar
      </source>
    </section>
  </section>

</body>
</document>
