<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>SSL Support</title>
</header>

<body>

  <p>The Grinder 3 supports the use of SSL by scripts.
  The Grinder 3 implements SSL using the Java Secure Socket
  Extension (JSSE) included in the Java run time. When used with
  the HTTP Plug-in, this is as simple as using <code>https</code>
  instead of <code>http</code> in URIs. Scripts can obtain a suitable
  <code>SSLContext</code> and hence a <code>SSLSocketFactory</code>
  for non-HTTP use cases, and can control the allocation of SSL
  sessions to worker threads.</p>

  <section>
    <title>Before we begin</title>

    <section>
      <title>Performance</title>

      <p>Simulating multiple SSL sessions on a single test machine may
      or may not be realistic. A typical browser running on a desktop
      PC has the benefit of a powerful CPU to run the SSL
      cryptography. Be careful that your results aren't constrained
      due to inadequate test client CPU power.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Grinder's SSL implementation is not secure</title>

      <p>To reduce the client side performance overhead, The Grinder
      deliberately accelerates SSL initialisation by using a random
      number generator that is seeded with a fixed number. Further, no
      validation of server certificates is performed. Neither of these
      hinder SSL communication, but they do make it less secure.</p>

      <warning> No guarantee is made as to the cryptographic strength
      of any SSL communication using The Grinder.</warning>

      <p>This acceleration affects initialisation time only and should
      not affect timing information obtained using The Grinder.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Controlling when new SSL sessions are created</title>

    <p>By default The Grinder creates a new SSL session for each run
    carried out by each worker thread. This is in line with the usual
    convention of simulating a user session with a worker thread
    executing the part of the script defined by
    <code>TestRunner.__call__()</code>.</p>

    <p>Alternatively, scripts may wish to have an SSL session per
    worker thread, i.e. for each thread to reuse SSL sessions on
    subsequent executions of <code>TestRunner.__call__()</code>. This
    can be done with the
    <code>SSLControl.setShareContextBetweenRuns()</code> method:</p>

<source class="jython">
from net.grinder.script.Grinder import grinder
grinder.SSLControl.shareContextBetweenRuns = 1
</source>

    <p>This will cause each worker thread to reuse SSL sessions
    between runs. SSL sessions will still not be shared between worker
    threads. Calling <code>setShareContextBetweenRuns()</code> affects
    all of the worker threads.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using client certificates</title>

    <p>If a server requests or requires a client certificate, The
    Grinder must have some way of providing one - this involves
    specifying a key store.</p>

<source class="jython">
from net.grinder.script.Grinder import grinder

class TestRunner:
    def __call__(self):
        grinder.SSLControl.setKeyStoreFile("mykeystore.jks", "passphrase")
</source>

    <p>It is only valid to use <code>setKeyStoreFile</code> from a
    worker thread, and it only affects that worker thread.</p>

    <p>There is also a method called <code>setKeyStore</code> which
    takes a <code>java.io.InputStream</code> which may be useful if
    your key store doesn't live on the local file system. Both methods
    have an overloaded version that allows the key store type to be
    specified, otherwise the default type is used (normally
    <code>jks</code>).</p>

    <p>Whenever <code>setKeyStoreFile</code>,
    <code>setKeyStore</code>, or <code>setKeyManagers</code> (see
    below) is called, the current SSL session for the thread is
    discarded. Consequently, you usually want to call these methods at
    the beginning of your <code>__call__()</code> method or from the
    <code>TestRunner.__init__()</code> constructor. Setting the
    thread's key store in <code>TestRunner.__init__()</code> is
    especially recommended if you calling
    <code>setShareContextBetweenRuns(true)</code> to share SSL
    sessions between runs.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>FAQ</title>

    <p>The astute reader who is familiar with key stores may have a
    few questions. Here's a mini FAQ:</p>

    <ol>
      <li>
        <p><em>If I have several suitable certificates in my key
        store, how does The Grinder chose between them?</em></p>

        <p>The Grinder relies on the JVM's default
        <code>KeyManager</code> implementations. This picks a
        certificate from the store based on SSL negotiation with the
        server. If there are several suitable certificates, the only
        way to control which is used is to <a
        href="#own-key-manager">provide your own
        <code>KeyManager</code></a>.</p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p><em><code>setKeyStoreFile</code> has a parameter for the
        key store password. What about the pass phrase that protects
        the private key in the key store?</em></p>

        <p>The pass phrases for keys must be the same as the key store
        password. This is a restriction of the default
        <code>KeyManager</code>s. If you don't like this, you can <a
        href="#own-key-manager">provide your own
        <code>KeyManager</code></a>.</p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p><em>Shouldn't I need to specify a set of certificates for
        trusted Certificate Authorities?</em></p>

        <p>No. The Grinder does not validate certificates received from
        the server, so does not need a set of CA certificates.</p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p><em>Can I use the properties
        <code>javax.net.ssl.keyStore</code>,
        <code>javax.net.ssl.keyStoreType</code>, and
        <code>javax.net.ssl.keyStorePassword</code> to specify a
        global keystore?</em>
  </p>

  <p>No. The Grinder does not use these properties, primarily
        because the JSSE does not provide a way to access its default
        SSLContext.</p>
       </li>
    </ol>
  </section>

  <section id="own-key-manager">
    <title>Picking a certificate from a key store [Advanced]</title>

    <p>Here's an example script that provides its own
    <code>X509KeyManager</code> implementation which controls which
    client certificate to use. The example is hard coded to always use
    the certificate with the alias <code>myalias</code>.</p>

<source class="jython">
from com.sun.net.ssl import KeyManagerFactory,X509KeyManager
from java.io import FileInputStream
from java.security import KeyStore
from jarray import array

class MyManager(X509KeyManager):
    def __init__(self, keyStoreFile, keyStorePassword):
        keyStore = KeyStore.getInstance("jks")
        keyStore.load(FileInputStream(keyStoreFile), keyStorePassword)

        keyManagerFactory = \
         KeyManagerFactory.getInstance(KeyManagerFactory.getDefaultAlgorithm())
        keyManagerFactory.init(keyStore, keyStorePassword)

        # Assume we have one key manager.
        self._delegate = keyManagerFactory.keyManagers[0]

    def __getattr__(self, a):
        """Some Python magic to pass on all invocations of methods we
        don't define on to our delegate."""

        if self.__dict__.has_key(a): return self.__dict__[a]
        else: return getattr(self._delegate, a)

    def chooseClientAlias(self, keyTypes, issuers):
        return "myalias"

myManager = MyManager("keystore.jks", "password")
myManagerArray = array((myManager,), X509KeyManager)

class TestRunner:
    def __call__(self):
        grinder.SSLControl.setKeyManagers(myManagerArray)
        # ...
</source>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Debugging</title>

    <p>When debugging SSL interactions, you may find it useful to set
    the following in <code>grinder.properties</code>.</p>

<source class="sh">
grinder.jvm.arguments=-Djavax.net.debug=ssl
# or -Djavax.net.debug=all
</source>

  </section>

</body>
</document>
