<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>Statistics</title>
</header>
<body>

  <section>
    <title>Standard statistics</title>

    <p>Details of the statistics provided by The Grinder can be found in
      the documentation of the <a
      href="site:api/Statistics">Statistics</a>
      interface. Scripts can use this interface to:
    </p>

    <ul>
     <li>Query whether a test was successful</li>
     <li>Obtain statistic values, such as the test time of the last test</li>
     <li>Modify or set a test's statistics before they are sent to the
        log and the console</li>
     <li>Report custom statistics</li>
     <li>Register additional views of standard and custom statistics</li>
    </ul>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Distribution of statistics</title>

    <p>All the statistics displayed in the console are aggregates
    (totals or averages) of a number of tests received in the
    appropriate period. The reason for this is efficiency. The
    Grinder would not perform or scale if every data point was
    transferred back to the console.</p>

    <p>The only place per-test statistics are available is in the
    process <code>data_*</code> files.</p>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Querying and updating statistics</title>

    <p>A script can query the statistics about the last completed test
    using <a href="site:api/Statistics/getForLastTest">
    grinder.statistics.forLastTest</a>. Script code instrumented by a test can access
    information about the statistics for the test (which may be incomplete) using
    <a href="site:api/Statistics/getForCurrentTest">
    grinder.statistics.forCurrentTest</a>. For details of the query
    and update methods, see
    <a href="site:api/StatisticsForTest">
    StatisticsForTest</a>. Refer to the documentation of the <a
    href="site:api/Statistics">Statistics</a> interface for other
    details.</p>

    <p>An <a href="site:script-gallery/statistics">example script</a>
    demonstrating these APIs can be found in the Script Gallery.</p>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Registering new expressions</title>

    <p>Custom statistic expressions can be added to console views and
    the worker process summary tables (found in the <code>out_*</code>
    log files) using the <a
    href="site:api/Statistics/registerSummaryExpression">registerSummaryExpression</a>
    method.</p>

    <p>Custom expressions can be added to worker process
    <code>data_*</code> using the <a
    href="site:api/Statistics/registerDataLogExpression">registerDataLogExpression</a>
    method.</p>

    <p>Both methods take a <em>displayName</em> and an <em>expression</em> as
    parameters.</p>

    <p>The <em>displayName</em> is the label used for the expression. For
    expressions displayed in the console, this string is converted to a key for
    an internationalised resource bundle look up by prefixing the string with
    <code>statistic.</code> and replacing any whitespace with underscores; if
    no value for the key exists, the raw display name string is used.</p>

    <p>Expressions are composed of statistic names (see <a
    href="site:api/Statistics">Statistics</a>) in a simple post-fix
    format using the symbols +, -, / and *, which have their usual
    meanings, in conjunction with simple statistic names or
    sub-expressions. Precedence is controlled by grouping expressions
    in parentheses. For example, the error rate is <code>(* (/ errors
    period) 1000)</code> errors per second. The symbol
    <code>sqrt</code> can be used to calculate the square root of an
    expression.</p>

    <p>Sample statistics, such as <code>timedTests</code>, must be introduced
    with one of <code>sum</code>, <code>count</code>, or <code>variance</code>,
    depending on the attribute of interest. For example, the statistic
    <code>expression (/ (sum timedTests) (count timedTests))</code> gives
    the mean test time in milliseconds.</p>

  </section>

</body>
</document>
