<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>The TCPProxy</title>
</header>

<body>
  <p>The TCPProxy is a proxy process that you can place in a TCP
  stream, such as the HTTP connection between your browser and a
  server. It filters the request and response streams, sending the
  results to the terminal window (<code>stdout</code>). You can
  control its behaviour by specifying different filters.</p>

  <figure src="../images/tcpproxy.gif" width="762" height="340"
  alt="The TCPProxy"/>

  <p>The TCPProxy's main purpose is to automatically generate HTTP
  test scripts that can be replayed with The Grinder's HTTP plugin.
  Because the TCPProxy lets you see what's going on at a network level
  it is also very useful as a debugging tool in its own right.</p>

  <section id="starting-tcpproxy">
    <title>Starting the TCPProxy</title>

    <p>You start the TCPProxy with something like:</p>

<source class="sh">
CLASSPATH=/opt/grinder/lib/grinder.jar
export CLASSPATH

java net.grinder.TCPProxy
</source>

    <p>Say <code>java net.grinder.TCPProxy -?</code> to get a full
    list of the command line options.</p>

    <p>With no additional options, the TCPProxy will start and display
    the following information:</p>

<source class="text">
Initialising as an HTTP/HTTPS proxy with the parameters:
   Request filters:  EchoFilter
   Response filters: EchoFilter
   Local address:    localhost:8001
Engine initialised, listening on port 8001
</source>

    <p>This indicates that the TCPProxy is listening as an HTTP proxy
    on port <code>8001</code> (the default, but you can change it with
    <code>-localPort</code>).</p>

    <p>The TCPProxy appears to your browser just like any other HTTP
    proxy server, and you can use your browser as normal. If you type
    <code>http://grinder.sourceforge.net</code> into your browser it
    will display The Grinder home page and the TCPProxy will output
    all of the HTTP interactions between the browser and the
    SourceForge site.</p>

    <p>The TCPProxy will proxy both HTTP and HTTPS. See <a
    href="#ssl">below</a> for details on customising the SSL
    configuration.</p>

  </section>

  <section id="BrowserPreparation">
    <title>Preparing the Browser</title>

    <p>You should now set your browser connection
    settings to specify the TCPProxy as the HTTP proxy. In the browser
    options dialog, set the proxy host to be the host on which the
    TCPProxy is running and proxy port to be <code>8001</code>).</p>

    <figure src="../images/proxy-preferences.png" width="562"
    height="462" alt="Browser proxy preferences"/>

  <p>The relevant options dialog can be accessed by the following steps:</p>
  <p><strong>MSIE</strong>: Tools -> Internet Options -> Connections -> Local Area Network Settings. <br />
  <strong>Mozilla/Netscape</strong>: Edit -> Preferences -> Advanced - Proxies.<br />
  <strong>Mozilla/Firefox</strong>: Tools -> Options -> General -> Connection Settings.<br />
  <strong>Opera</strong>: Tools -> Preferences -> Advanced -> Network -> Proxy Servers.</p>
  <p>It is important to remember to remove any "bypass proxy server" or "No Proxy for" settings
  that you might have so that all the traffic flows through the TCPProxy and can
  be captured.</p>

  <p>It might also be a good idea to clear out any cache/temporary Internet files that
    might be on your workstation. On the other hand, you might decide not to do
    this if you want to record a script representing a frequent user to your
    site who has images are <a href="site:gfaq/common/http-caching">resources in
    their browser cache</a>. Also for IE users,
    changing the temporary Internet files settings to check for a newer version
    on every visit to a page can be useful.</p>

  <figure src="../images/ie-cache-settings.png" width="354" height="351"
    alt="Temporary Internet Files Settings in IE"/>

  </section>

  <section id="EchoFilter">
    <title>Using the EchoFilter</title>

    <p>The EchoFilter is the default filter used by the TCPProxy if no options are specified
  in the startup command. The EchoFilter outputs the stream activity to the terminal. It
    can be very useful for debugging as described in <a
    href="site:use-the-tcpproxy">this FAQ</a>.</p>

    <p>Bytes that do not have a printable ASCII representation are
    displayed in hexadecimal between square brackets. Here's some
    example output:</p>

    <source class="text">
------ 127.0.0.1:2263->ads.osdn.com:80 ------
GET /?ad_id=5839&amp;alloc_id=12703&amp;site_id=2&amp;request_id=8320720&amp;1102173982760 HTTP/1.1
Host: ads.osdn.com
User-Agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Windows; U; Windows NT 5.0; en-US; rv:1.7.5) Gecko/20041107 Firefox/1.0
Accept: image/png,*/*;q=0.5
Accept-Language: en-gb,en-us;q=0.7,en;q=0.3
Accept-Encoding: gzip,deflate
Accept-Charset: ISO-8859-1,utf-8;q=0.7,*;q=0.7
Keep-Alive: 300
Proxy-Connection: keep-alive
Referer: http://sourceforge.net/projects/grinder


--- ads.osdn.com:80->127.0.0.1:2263 opened --
------ ads.osdn.com:80->127.0.0.1:2273 ------
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Date: Sat, 04 Dec 2004 15:26:27 GMT
Server: Apache/1.3.29 (Unix) mod_gzip/1.3.26.1a mod_perl/1.29
Pragma: no-cache
Cache-control: private
Connection: close
Transfer-Encoding: chunked
Content-Type: image/gif


------ ads.osdn.com:80->127.0.0.1:2273 ------
80B
GIF89ae[00])[00D50000C3C3C3FEFDFD]hhhVVVyyy[F5CCD2D4D4D4CBCBCBD7]'F
    </source>

    <p>Information lines are displayed to indicate the end point
    addresses and direction of the information flow and also whether a
    connection has just been opened or closed.</p>

  </section>

  <section id="HTTPPluginTCPProxyFilter">
    <title>Using the HTTP TCPProxy filters</title>

    <p>You can use the TCPProxy to generate an HTTP script
    suitable for use with The Grinder. The Grinder provides a pair
    of HTTP filters for this purpose. These filters are enabled by the
    <code>-http</code> command line option.</p>

  <p>The first step is to start the TCPProxy with an HTTP filter:</p>

<source class="sh">
java net.grinder.TCPProxy -console -http > grinder.py
</source>

  <p>The <code>&gt; grinder.py</code> part of the line sends the script to a
  file called <code>grinder.py</code>.</p>

  <p>The terminal output of the TCPProxy looks like:</p>

<source class="text">
14/03/06 17:04:25 (tcpproxy): Initialising as an HTTP/HTTPS proxy with the
parameters:
   Request filters:    HTTPRequestFilter
   Response filters:   HTTPResponseFilter
   Local address:      localhost:8001
14/03/06 17:04:27 (tcpproxy): Engine initialised, listening on port 8001
</source>

  <p>The console (initiated by <em>-console</em>) displays a simple control window that allows the TCPProxy
   to be shut down cleanly. This is needed because some terminal shells, e.g. Cygwin bash,
   do not allow Java processes to be interrupted cleanly, so filters cannot rely
   on standard shut down hooks. The console also allows a user to add ad-hoc commentary to the script
   during the recording. The console looks like this:</p>

  <figure src="../images/tcpproxy-console.png" width="503" height="60"
    alt="TCPProxy Console"/>

  <p>The TCPProxy console will be incorporated into the main <a href="site:console">console</a> in
  a future release.</p>

  <p>Set your browser to use the TCPProxy as
  the HTTP proxy as <a href="#BrowserPreparation">described earlier</a>),
  and run through your test scenario on your website.</p>

  <p>Having finished your run through, press "Stop" on the TCPProxy
  console and the generated script will be written to <code>grinder.py</code>.</p>

    <p>The <code>grinder.py</code> file contains headers, requests and
  a logical grouping of requests into pages, of the recorded tests.</p>
    <p>For example, the headers section:</p>

<source class="jython">

# The Grinder 3.11-SNAPSHOT
# HTTP script recorded by TCPProxy at 05-Jul-2012 09:20:55

from net.grinder.script import Test
from net.grinder.script.Grinder import grinder
from net.grinder.plugin.http import HTTPPluginControl, HTTPRequest
from HTTPClient import NVPair
connectionDefaults = HTTPPluginControl.getConnectionDefaults()
httpUtilities = HTTPPluginControl.getHTTPUtilities()

# To use a proxy server, uncomment the next line and set the host and port.
# connectionDefaults.setProxyServer("localhost", 8001)

def createRequest(test, url, headers=None):
    """Create an instrumented HTTPRequest."""
    request = HTTPRequest(url=url)
    if headers: request.headers=headers
    test.record(request, HTTPRequest.getHttpMethodFilter())
    return request

# These definitions at the top level of the file are evaluated once,
# when the worker process is started.

connectionDefaults.defaultHeaders = \
  [ NVPair('Accept-Encoding', 'gzip, deflate'),
    NVPair('Accept-Language', 'en-gb,en;q=0.5'),
    NVPair('Cache-Control', 'no-cache'),
    NVPair('User-Agent', 'Mozilla/5.0 (X11; Ubuntu; Linux x86_64; rv:13.0) Gecko/20100101 Firefox/13.0.1'), ]

headers0= \
  [ NVPair('Accept', 'text/css,*/*;q=0.1'),
    NVPair('Referer', 'http://grinder.sourceforge.net/'), ]

headers1= \
  [ NVPair('Accept', '*/*'),
    NVPair('Referer', 'http://grinder.sourceforge.net/'), ]

headers2= \
  [ NVPair('Accept', 'image/png,image/*;q=0.8,*/*;q=0.5'),
    NVPair('Referer', 'http://grinder.sourceforge.net/'), ]

headers3= \
  [ NVPair('Accept', 'image/png,image/*;q=0.8,*/*;q=0.5'),
    NVPair('Referer', 'http://grinder.sourceforge.net/skin/screen.css'), ]

headers4= \
  [ NVPair('Accept', 'image/png,image/*;q=0.8,*/*;q=0.5'),
    NVPair('Referer', 'http://grinder.sourceforge.net/skin/profile.css'), ]

#....
</source>

    <p>In the requests section, a request object for each unique URL
    is created:</p>

<source class="jython">
url0 = 'http://grinder.sourceforge.net:80'
url1 = 'http://www.ohloh.net:80'
url2 = 'http://sourceforge.net:80'

request101 = createRequest(Test(101, 'GET /'), url0)

request102 = createRequest(Test(102, 'GET profile.css'), url0, headers0)

request103 = createRequest(Test(103, 'GET screen.css'), url0, headers0)

request104 = createRequest(Test(104, 'GET print.css'), url0, headers0)

# ...
</source>

    <p>Note the use of the <code>createRequest</code> helper function,
    which was defined earlier. This function creates a
    <code>HTTPRequest</code> object and instruments its
    <code>GET</code>, <code>POST</code>, ..., methods to report
    call statistics against the supplied <code>Test</code>.</p>

    <p>Finally the TestRunner class. This section groups the requests
    into pages and defines each page as a method, sets the sleep
    interval between requests, and provides an instrumented method for
    the return of data from the tests: </p>

<source class="jython">
  # A method for each recorded page.
  def page1(self):
    """GET / (requests 101-131)."""
    result = request101.GET('/', None,
      ( NVPair('Accept', 'text/html,application/xhtml+xml,application/xml;q=0.9,*/*;q=0.8'), ))
    self.token_subject = \
      httpUtilities.valueFromBodyURI('subject') # 'Feedback on The Grinder web site index.h...'
    self.token_sitesearch = \
      httpUtilities.valueFromHiddenInput('sitesearch') # 'grinder.sourceforge.net'

    grinder.sleep(176)
    request102.GET('/skin/profile.css')

    request103.GET('/skin/screen.css')

    request104.GET('/skin/print.css')

    request105.GET('/skin/basic.css')

#.....

    return result

  def page2(self):

#.....

  def __call__(self):
    """Called for every run performed by the worker thread."""
    self.page1()      # GET / (requests 101-131)

    grinder.sleep(39)
    self.page2()      # GET project_users.js (requests 201-202)
    self.page3()      # GET pdfdoc.gif (requests 301-305)
    self.page4()      # GET sflogo.php (request 401)
    self.page5()      # GET external-link.gif (request 501)


# Instrument page methods.
Test(100, 'Page 1').record(TestRunner.page1)
Test(200, 'Page 2').record(TestRunner.page2)

#.....
</source>

    <p>Once you've recorded your script you have two methods
  that you can use to replay your script:</p>

  <ol>

  <li>You can create a simple
    <a href="site:properties"><code>grinder.properties</code></a>
    file and you can replay the recorded scenario with The Grinder.
    Your properties file should at least set <code>grinder.script</code> to
    <code>grinder.py</code>.</li>

  <li>Alternately you can use the console to <a
  href="site:g3/console/ui/script-tab">distribute your script to an
  agent and set it as the script to run</a>. Each agent will still
  need a simple <a
  href="site:properties"><code>grinder.properties</code></a> file
  containing the console address, though you will not need to set the
  <code>grinder.script</code> property.</li>

  </ol>

  <p>The recorded script grinder.py can be edited by hand to suit your needs.</p>

  <section id="clojure-script">
    <title>Generating a Clojure script</title>

  <p>You can generate a Clojure script using <code>-http
  clojure</code> on the command line. For example:</p>

<source class="sh">java net.grinder.TCPProxy -http clojure -console</source>

  </section>



  <section id="Stylesheets">
    <title>Altering the output with custom stylesheet</title>

  <p>The TCPProxy HTTP filters installed with
  <code>-http</code>, <code>-http jython</code>, and <code>-http
  clojure</code>, each create their output by transforming an XML
  model of the HTTP request/response stream using an XLST
  stylesheet.</p>

  <p>These standard stylesheets can be found in <code>etc</code>. You
  can use a stylesheet of of your own making to customise the output
  of the filter. You should pass the file name of your custom
  stylesheet as a command line argument directly after
  <code>-http</code>.</p>

  <p>If you want to see the intermediate XML model you can use:</p>

<source class="sh">java net.grinder.TCPProxy -http etc/httpToXML.xsl -console</source>

  <p>The model confirms to the XML schema <code>etc/tcpproxy-http.xsd</code>.</p>
  </section>

  <section id="offset-test-numbers">
    <title>How to offset test numbers</title>
   <p>
   If sometimes useful to offset test numbers for a test script when
running several different scripts together, perhaps using the
<a href="site:script-gallery/sequence">sequence</a>, or
<a href="site:script-gallery/parallel">parallel</a> examples
from the script gallery. This gives the tests contributed by each script
a distinct range of test numbers, which is important because the test
number uniquely identifies the test in the console and the data logs.</p>

<p>The HTTP TCPProxy filter allows the recording of a test script with
off-setting test numbers. This is done using the
<code>HTTPPlugin.initialTest</code> property, which can either be set
directly on the command line, or in a file using the
<code>-properties</code> option. Here's an example that will start the
test numbers at 1000:</p>

<source class="sh">java -DHTTPPlugin.initialTest=1000  net.grinder.TCPProxy  -http</source>

<p>Its also simple to offset test values by modifying the script.</p>

<p>Edit the recorded script to replace:</p>
<source class="jython">
from net.grinder.script import Test
</source>

<p>with:</p>

<source class="jython">
from net.grinder.script import Test as StandardTest

def Test(number, description):
    # Adjust the 1000 to the appropriate offset.
    return StandardTest(number + 1000, description)
</source>


<p>Neither technique allows different test scripts to be merged
together into one because you also have to alter the identifiers used
for headers, URLs, pages, tokens, and so on. If you want to do this,
you might consider a <a href="#Stylesheets"> custom
stylesheet</a>.</p>

  </section>


  <section id="additional-headers">
    <title>How to record additional headers</title>

    <p>By default, the following HTTP headers are recorded from the
    HTTP stream.</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Accept</li>
      <li>Accept-Charset</li>
      <li>Accept-Encoding</li>
      <li>Accept-Language</li>
      <li>Cache-Control</li>
      <li>Referer</li>
      <li>User-Agent</li>
      <li>Content-Type</li>
      <li>If-Modified-Since</li>
      <li>If-None-Match</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Additional headers can be specified with the
    <code>HTTPPlugin.additionalHeaders</code> system property. The
    value is a comma-separated list of header names. For example:</p>

<source class="sh">java net.grinder.TCPProxy -DHTTPPlugin.additionalHeaders=MyHeader,AnotherHeaderName -http</source>

  </section>

  </section>

  <section id="ssl">
    <title>SSL and HTTPS support</title>

    <p>The TCPProxy has SSL support based on Java's <a
    href="ext:oracle/java/jsse">JSSE</a> framework.</p>

    <p>SSL relationships are necessarily point to point. When you
    interpose the TCPProxy in SSL communications between a browser and
    a server you end up with two SSL connections. Each SSL connection
    has its own set of client and server certificates (both of which
    are optional).</p>

    <figure src="../images/tcpproxy-ssl.gif" width="762" height="200"
    alt="TCPProxy and SSL"/>

    <p>The TCPProxy will negotiate appropriate certificates for both
    connections using built-in certificates or those from a
    user-specified Java key store. In particular, the TCPProxy needs a
    self-signed server certificate for the connection from the
    browser. By default, the TCPProxy will use a built-in
    certificate.</p>

    <p>When first establishing a connection, your browser will present
    a warning and confirmation dialog. This is because the built-in
    certificate isn't authorised by any of the certificate authorities
    that the browser trusts. Additionally, the built-in certificate
    authorises <code>localhost</code> so if your server doesn't
    listen at this address the browser will complain. Choose the
    "accept this certificate for this session" option.</p>

    <warning>The Grinder deliberately accelerates SSL initialisation
    by using a random number generator that is seeded with a fixed
    number. This does not hinder SSL communication, but theoretically
    makes it less secure. No guarantee is made as to the
    cryptographic strength of any SSL communication using The
    Grinder.</warning>

    <p>Advanced users can specify their own server certificate for the
    connection from the browser, or add client certificates for the
    connection to the server, using the <code>-keystore</code>,
    <code>-keystorepassword</code>, and <code>-keystoretype</code>
    options. See the J2SE/JSSE documentation for how to set up a key
    store.</p>

    <p>If you fail to provide a key store with a valid server
    certificate (hard to do now The Grinder has a built in
    certificate), you may get a <em>No available certificate
    corresponds to the SSL cipher suites which are enabled</em>
    exception, and your browser may report that it cannot communicate
    as it has no common encryption algorithms. Internet Explorer likes
    to be different. If start the TCPProxy without a valid server
    certificate and then connect through it using Internet Explorer,
    the TCPProxy will report "SSL peer shut down incorrectly. The
    browser will just spin away until it times out. The easiest way to
    provide a server certificate is to copy the <em>testkeys</em> file
    from the <a href="ext:oracle/java/jsse-archive">JSSE samples
    distribution</a> and start the proxy using:</p>

<source class="sh">
java net.grinder.TCPProxy -keyStore testkeys -keyStorePassword passphrase
</source>
  </section>

  <section id="chained-proxies">
    <title>Using the TCPProxy with other proxies</title>

    <p>The TCPProxy can be used with other HTTP/HTTPS proxies.</p>

    <figure src="../images/tcpproxy-proxy.gif" width="762"
    height="172" alt="Chained proxies"/>

    <p>Use the <code>-httpproxy</code> option to specify the host name
    and port of the proxy. Use the <code>-httpsproxy</code> option
    only if your HTTPS proxy requires separate settings.</p>
  </section>

  <section id="port-forwarding-mode">
    <title>Using the TCPProxy as a port forwarder</title>

    <p>It is normally most useful to use the TCPProxy in its HTTP
    Proxy mode as described above.</p>

    <p>When using the TCPProxy as a debugging tool it occasionally is
    useful to use it in <em>port forwarding</em> mode. This mode is
    enabled when one or more of <code>-remotehost</code> and
    <code>-remoteport</code> are specified. In port forwarding mode,
    the TCPProxy simply listens on <code>localhost:localport</code>
    and forwards to <code>remotehost:remoteport</code>.</p>

    <p>To understand why HTTP Proxy mode is usually better than port
    forwarding mode when using a browser, consider what happens if the
    remote server returns a page with an absolute URL link back to
    itself. If you click on the link, the browser will contact the
    server directly, bypassing the TCPProxy. Another disadvantage is
    that you can't use the TCPProxy with more than one remote
    sever.</p>
  </section>

  <section id="options-summary">
    <title>Summary of TCPProxy options</title>

    <table>
    <tr>
      <th>Option</th>
      <th>Description</th>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><strong>Commonly used options</strong></td>

      <td></td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-console</code></td>

      <td>Display a simple console that has a control button that
      allows The TCPProxy to be shut down cleanly. This can help in
      certain situations where a hard kill of the TCPProxy process
      would lose output that is still buffered in memory.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-http [stylesheet]</code></td>

      <td>Adds a standard request filter and response filter to
      produce a Jython script for The Grinder suitable for use with
      the HTTP plugin. The default filter generates a Jython script
      and is equivalent to <code>-http jython</code>. Alternatively,
      use <code>clojure</code> to produce a Clojure script, or the
      output can be customised completely by providing the file name
      of an XSLT style sheet.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-requestfilter filter</code></td>

      <td>Add a request filter. <code>filter</code> can be the name of
      a class that implements
      <code>net.grinder.tools.tcpproxy.TCPProxyFilter</code> or one of
      <code>NONE</code>, <code>ECHO</code>. The option can be
      specified multiple times, in which case the filters are invoked
      one after another. If the not specified, the default
      <code>ECHO</code> filter is used.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-responsefilter filter</code></td>

      <td>Add a response filter. <code>filter</code> can be the name
      of a class that implements
      <code>net.grinder.tools.tcpproxy.TCPProxyFilter</code> or one of
      <code>NONE</code>, <code>ECHO</code>. The option can be
      specified multiple times, in which case the filters are invoked
      one after another. If the not specified, the default
      <code>ECHO</code> filter is used.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-localhost host</code></td>

      <td>Set the host name or IP address to listen on. This must
      correspond to an interface of the machine the TCPProxy is
      started on. The default is <code>localhost</code>.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-localport port</code></td>

      <td>Set the port to listen on. The default is
      <code>8001</code>.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-keystore file</code></td>

      <td>Specify a custom key store. Usually the built-in keystore is
      good enough so <code>-keystore</code> does not need to be
      specified.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-keystorepassword password</code></td>

      <td>Set the key store password. Only used if
      <code>-keystore</code> is set. Optional for some key store
      types.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-keystoretype type</code></td>

      <td>Set the key store type. Only used if <code>-keystore</code>
      is set. If not specified, the default value depends on JSSE
      configuration but is usually <code>jks</code>.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><strong>Less frequently used options</strong></td>

      <td></td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-properties file</code></td>

      <td>Specify a file containing properties that are passed on to
      the filters.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-remotehost host</code></td>

      <td>Set the host name or port the TCPProxy should connect to in
      <a href="#port-forwarding-mode">port forwarding mode</a>. The
      TCPProxy starts in port forwarding mode if either
      <code>-remotehost</code> or <code>-remoteport</code> is set. The
      default is <code>localhost</code>.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-remoteport port</code></td>

      <td>Set the port the TCPProxy should connect to in <a
      href="#port-forwarding-mode">port forwarding mode</a>. The
      TCPProxy starts in port forwarding mode if either
      <code>-remotehost</code> or <code>-remoteport</code> is set. The
      default is <code>7001</code>.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-timeout seconds</code></td>

      <td>Set an idle timeout. This is how long the TCPProxy will wait
      for a request before timing out and freeing the local port. The
      TCPProxy will not time out if there are active connections.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-httpproxy host port</code></td>

      <td>Specify that output should be directed through <a
      href="#chained-proxies">another HTTP/HTTPS proxy</a>. This may
      help you reach the Internet. This option is not supported in <a
      href="#port-forwarding-mode">port forwarding mode</a>.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-httpsproxy host port</code></td>

      <td>Specify that output should be directed through a HTTPS
      proxy. Overrides any <code>-httpproxy </code> setting. This
      option is not supported in <a href="#port-forwarding-mode">port
      forwarding mode</a>.</td>
    </tr>


    <tr>
      <td><code>-ssl</code></td>

      <td>Use SSL in <a href="#port-forwarding-mode">port forwarding
      mode</a>. This will make both the TCPProxy's local socket and
      the connections to the target server use SSL. The default
      <em>HTTP Proxy mode</em> ignores this option and always listens
      as an HTTP proxy and an HTTPS proxy.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-colour</code></td>

      <td>Specify that a simple colour scheme should be used to
      distinguish request streams from response schemes. This uses
      terminal control codes that only work on ANSI compliant
      terminals.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-component class</code></td>

      <td>Register a component class with the filter PicoContainer.</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td><code>-debug</code></td>

      <td>Make PicoContainer chatty.</td>
    </tr>

    </table>
  </section>

</body>
</document>
