<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>Weighted Distribution Of Tests</title>
</header>

<body>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p>
    This is a step-by-step tutorial on how to schedule tests
    according to any "weight distribution" you desire.  This is an
    exercise in data structures and random numbers, and as such it does
    not use any facilities of The Grinder (such as HTTPClient) except for its
    core TestRunner functionality.  Therefore, it is immediately applicable
    to almost any test scenario.
    </p>
    <p><strong>Walt Tuvell</strong></p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Statement Of The Problem</title>
    <p>
    Let's assume you have a collection of four kinds of tests you want to
    run, say CREATE, READ, UPDATE, DELETE.  These might be operations on
    a Web Server, or a Database Server, for example.
    </p>
    <p>
    Suppose further you want to run your tests using many threads
    (grinder.threads property in the grinder.properties file), and
    you want to schedule these threads amongst the tests according
    to a specified "weighted distribution".  As an example, we'll assume
    you want to run: 20% CREATEs, 40% READs, 30% UPDATEs, 10% DELETEs.
    </p>
    <p>
    How can you do this?
    </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Test Cases</title>
    <p>
    Note that the problem statement is independent of the actual tests
    themselves.  So for illustrative purposes, we will choose dummy tests
    that simply print a message to stdout.  (Your tests will likely make
    use of deeper facilities of The Grinder, such as HTTPClient, etc.)
    </p>
    <source class="jython">
    def doCREATEtest():
        print 'Doing CREATE test ...'
    def doREADtest():
        print 'Doing READ   test ...'
    def doUPDATEtest():
        print 'Doing UPDATE test ...'
    def doDELETEtest():
        print 'Doing DELETE test ...'
    </source>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Weight Distribution Definition</title>
    <p>
    The most flexible way to define test distribution is by means of "relative
    weights", that is, numbers which specify the number of times each
    test is to be run relative to one another (as opposed to an absolute
    number of runs - for that, see the grinder.runs property in the
    grinder.properties file).
    </p>
    <p>
    For our example, we begin by defining our desired weight distribution
    in a table (Jython dictionary structure) like the following:
    </p>
    <source class="jython">
    g_Weights = {
        'CREATE': 2,
        'READ'  : 4,
        'UPDATE': 3,
        'DELETE': 1,
    }
    </source>
    <p>
    Since the weights in this table are relative, we could multiply
    all their values by a constant and arrive at the same weight
    distribution.  (The same goes for division, provided we end up with
    integers.)  If the sum of weights adds up to 100, the weights can be
    interpreted directly as "percentages".  For example, in our example,
    if we multiplied our weights by 10, we'd end up with exactly the
    percentage values in the original statement of our example.
    </p>
    <p>
    Note that string-names in the weight table are arbitrary tags (they will
    be mapped to the tests in TestRunner.__call__()).  As a matter of style,
    the weight table should be placed near the top of your script,
    so its settings can be modified easily from run to run, according to
    the test scenarios you want to model.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Accumulator Function</title>
    <p>
    All the magic of choosing which test to run according to your specified
    weight distribution is accomplished by the following "accumulator" function:
    </p>
    <source class="jython">
    def weightAccumulator(i_dict):
        keyList = i_dict.keys()
        keyList.sort()  # sorting is optional - order coming-in doesn't matter, but determinism is kinda cool
        listAcc = []
        weightAcc = 0
        for key in keyList:
            weightAcc += i_dict[key]
            listAcc.append((key, weightAcc))
        return (listAcc, weightAcc)  # order going-out does matter - hence "listAcc" instead of "dictAcc"

    g_WeightsAcc, g_WeightsAccMax = weightAccumulator(g_Weights)
    g_WeightsAccLen, g_WeightsAccMax_1 = len(g_WeightsAcc), g_WeightsAccMax-1
    </source>
    <p>
    This accumulator function takes a weight dictionary as input, and
    transforms it into an accumulated weight list, suitable for random
    indexing, as we will do below.
    </p>
    <p>
    As shown above, the accumulator function is called with g_Weights as
    input, and its output is captured in two convenience variables.  Two
    more convenience variables are also defined, for use below.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Random Numbers</title>
    <p>
    Next, we prepare a random number generator, which we will use to
    index into our accumulated weight list.  There are many choices
    available (including Jython), but for our purposes here we'll just
    use the Java standard generator:
    </p>
    <source class="jython">
    g_rng = java.util.Random(java.lang.System.currentTimeMillis())

    def randNum(i_min, i_max):
        assert i_min &lt;= i_max
        range = i_max - i_min + 1  # re-purposing "range" is legal in Python
        assert range &lt;= 0x7fffffff  # because we're using java.util.Random
        randnum = i_min + g_rng.nextInt(range)
        assert i_min &lt;= randnum &lt;= i_max
        return randnum
    </source>
    <p>
    Here, we've constructed a random number generator, and seeded it with
    the time-of-day.  (For test/simulation purposes, it is counterproductive
    to use secure random number generators, such as java.security.SecureRandom,
    or a secure seed source.)
    </p>
    <p>
    Further, we've defined a randNum() function that takes minimum and
    maximum values as input, and returns a random number between them (inclusive of
    both endpoints).
    </p>
    <p>
    Note: One advantage of using java.util.Random is that it's thread-safe,
    so we need construct only a single global generator.  But that safety
    comes at the expense of some performance loss, especially if you are
    using the generator extensively, such as generating massive random
    file/object content.  In that case, you may want to use faster,
    non-thread-safe generators, constructing one for each thread's private
    use.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Test Runner Class</title>
    <p>
    We are now ready to define our TestRunner class:
    </p>
    <source class="jython">
    class TestRunner:
        def __call__(self):
            opNum = randNum(0, g_WeightsAccMax_1)
            opType = None  # flag for assertion below
            for i in range(g_WeightsAccLen):
                if opNum &lt; g_WeightsAcc[i][1]:
                    opType = g_WeightsAcc[i][0]
                    break
            assert opType in g_Weights.keys()

            if   opType=='CREATE': doCREATEtest()
            elif opType=='READ'  : doREADtest()
            elif opType=='UPDATE': doUPDATEtest()
            elif opType=='DELETE': doDELETEtest()
            else                 : assert False
    </source>
    <p>
    According to The Grinder framework, every worker thread calls
    TestRunner.__call__() in an infinite loop (until it terminates).
    In our case, for each run, each thread first chooses a random number,
    opNum, and then uses that random number to index into the
    accumulated weight list.  (Well, it's not exactly "indexing" in the
    array or database access sense, but the idea is the same.)  This
    results in the tag of an operation type, opType, to be called.
    The thread then maps the operation type tag to a test, and calls it.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Putting It All Together</title>
    <p>
    Our example script is now complete, so we can run it.
    </p>
    <p>
    Let's say we want to do 10,000 runs.  In your grinder.properties file,
    set grinder.threads=20, grinder.runs=500.  Then invoke startAgent.sh.
    You'll see 10,000 lines printed, each saying "Doing XXX test ...",
    where XXX is one of CREATE, READ, UPDATE, DELETE.
    </p>
    <p>
    But did you get the weighted distribution of test cases you wanted?
    For that, you need to count various lines printed out by the test.
    In a Linux environment, you can do this conveniently by rerunning the
    test in a pipeline command as follows:
    </p>
    <source class="sh">
    startAgent.sh |  \
        awk '/^Doing /{count[$0]+=1} END{for (test in count) print test, count[test]}'
    </source>
    <p>
    A typical run of this command will produce results similar to the following:
    </p>
    <source class="text">
    Doing CREATE test ... 2006
    Doing READ   test ... 4045
    Doing UPDATE test ... 2993
    Doing DELETE test ... 956
    </source>
    <p>
    Inspection of these numbers shows you are indeed running the distribution
    you desired.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Full Script Listing</title>

<source class="jython">
import java.lang.System, java.util.Random


g_Weights = {
    'CREATE': 2,
    'READ'  : 4,
    'UPDATE': 3,
    'DELETE': 1,
}


def doCREATEtest():
    print 'Doing CREATE test ...'
def doREADtest():
    print 'Doing READ   test ...'
def doUPDATEtest():
    print 'Doing UPDATE test ...'
def doDELETEtest():
    print 'Doing DELETE test ...'


def weightAccumulator(i_dict):
    keyList = i_dict.keys()
    keyList.sort()  # sorting is optional - order coming-in doesn't matter, but determinism is kinda cool
    listAcc = []
    weightAcc = 0
    for key in keyList:
        weightAcc += i_dict[key]
        listAcc.append((key, weightAcc))
    return (listAcc, weightAcc)  # order going-out does matter - hence "listAcc" instead of "dictAcc"

g_WeightsAcc, g_WeightsAccMax = weightAccumulator(g_Weights)
g_WeightsAccLen, g_WeightsAccMax_1 = len(g_WeightsAcc), g_WeightsAccMax-1


g_rng = java.util.Random(java.lang.System.currentTimeMillis())

def randNum(i_min, i_max):
    assert i_min &lt;= i_max
    range = i_max - i_min + 1  # re-purposing "range" is legal in Python
    assert range &lt;= 0x7fffffff  # because we're using java.util.Random
    randnum = i_min + g_rng.nextInt(range)
    assert i_min &lt;= randnum &lt;= i_max
    return randnum


class TestRunner:
    def __call__(self):
        opNum = randNum(0, g_WeightsAccMax_1)
        opType = None  # flag for assertion below
        for i in range(g_WeightsAccLen):
            if opNum &lt; g_WeightsAcc[i][1]:
                opType = g_WeightsAcc[i][0]
                break
        assert opType in g_Weights.keys()

        if   opType=='CREATE': doCREATEtest()
        elif opType=='READ'  : doREADtest()
        elif opType=='UPDATE': doUPDATEtest()
        elif opType=='DELETE': doDELETEtest()
        else                 : assert False
</source>
  </section>

</body>
</document>
