<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>A Step-By-Step Script Tutorial</title>
</header>

<body>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>The is a step-by-step tutorial of how to write a number of
    dynamic HTTP tests using various aspects of The Grinder and Jython
    APIs. The test script contains a number of tests that are requests
    to the same URL. For each request, a different XML parameter is
    specified. The resulting HTML data is checked on return and if the
    test was not successful, the statistics API is used to mark that
    test as failed.</p>

    <p><strong>Richard Perks</strong></p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Script Imports</title>

<source class="jython">
import string
import random
from java.lang import String
from java.net import URLEncoder
from net.grinder.script import Test
from net.grinder.plugin.http import HTTPRequest
from net.grinder.common import GrinderException
</source>

    <p>Firstly when writing a script come the import statements. These
    include imports of standard Python modules such as
    <code>string</code> and <code>random</code>, and other Java
    imports including some language and network classes. Finally there
    are imports for Grinder specific methods. A powerful feature of
    the Jython scripts that are used with The Grinder is the ability
    to take a mix and match approach to script programming. In some
    cases using a Python API is quicker and easier than always using
    the corresponding Java API calls, so feel free to use whichever
    API makes most sense.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Test Definition</title>

<source class="jython">
tests = {
    "News01"      : Test(1, "News 1 posting"),
    "Sport01"     : Test(2, "Sport 1 posting"),
    "Sport02"     : Test(3, "Sport 2 posting"),
    "Trading01"   : Test(4, "Trading 1 query"),
    "LifeStyle01" : Test(5, "LifeStyle 1 posting"),
}
</source>

    <p>To keep the script code easy to read, we next define all the
    tests we are going to be running within this script. These are
    created as a Python dictionary and are name-value pairs. The name
    is the name of the test and the value is a <code>Test</code>
    object with a test numeric identifier and description.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Bread crumbs</title>

<source class="jython">
log = grinder.logger.info

# Server Properties
SERVER     = "http://serverhost:7001"
URI        = "/myServlet"
</source>

    <p>We next define some variables such as Grinder helper methods
    and server properties. The <code>log</code> variable is used to
    hold a reference to The Grinder logging mechanism and is used
    throughout the script.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Test Interface</title>

<source class="jython">
class TestRunner:
    def __call__(self):
</source>

    <p>Here is the definition of our test class and the method called
    by The Grinder by each test thread. All scripts must define this
    class and method. Whilst we are discussing classes and methods, an
    important point to remember when new to Jython script development
    is that Jython/Python code is scoped by indentation, rather than
    using braces like in a language like C or Java. The colon is used
    to delimit the start scope such as an <code>if</code> or method
    definition.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the Dictionary and Random Python Modules</title>

<source class="jython">
for idx in range(len(tests)):
       testId = random.choice(tests.keys())
       log("Reading XML file %s " % testId)
</source>

    <p>As discussed earlier, the use of Python modules is encouraged
    during Grinder script development and I have used a few examples
    above when performing the test run. Within the test run, each of
    the tests defined in the test dictionary is looped round so that
    each Grinder thread executes five separate tests. Within the loop,
    a test is chosen randomly from one of the five tests. This
    prevents all threads of executing all the tests in the same order
    and helps simulate a more random load on the server.</p>

    <p>Within the dictionary defined as <code>tests</code>, there are
    a number of useful methods such as are <code>keys()</code>,
    <code>items()</code> and <code>sort()</code>. We use the keys
    returned from the tests dictionary as the parameter to the
    <code>choice()</code> method in the random module. This randomly
    selects one of the tests keys as the current test identifier.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Forget the Java IO Package when Handling Files</title>

<source class="jython">
file = open("./CAAssets/"+testId+".xml", 'r')
fileStr = URLEncoder.encode(String(file.read()))
file.close()

requestString = "%s%s%s%s" % (SERVER, URI, "?xmldata=", fileStr)
</source>

    <p>When having to retrieve the contents of files using Jython
    script, the use of the file operations blitz's Java IO for pure
    script development speed. In the code above, we need to open an
    XML document that has the name of a test, for example
    <code>News01.xml</code>. This will be used as a request parameter
    for the News01 test. The file is opened for reading and encoded
    using the Java URLEncoder.</p>

    <p>We next construct the request string to the server by
    concatenating the server, URI and XML documents together.
    <em>Tip</em>: if you need to remove spaces from within a string,
    you can use a method like the following:</p>

<source class="jython">
requestString = string.join(requestString.split(), "")
</source>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Sending the Request and the Statistics API</title>

<source class="jython">
grinder.statistics.delayReports = 1
request = HTTPRequest()
tests[testId].record(request)

log("Sending request %s " % requestString)
result = request.GET(requestString)
</source>

    <p>As part of the test execution, we want the ability to check the
    result of the HTTP request. If the response back from the server
    is not one that we except, we want to mark the test as
    unsuccessful and not include the statistics in the test times. To
    do this, the <code>delayReports</code> variable can be set to 1.
    Doing so will delay the reporting back of the statistics until
    after the test has completed and we have had chance to check its
    operation. The default is to report back when the test returns
    control back to the script, i.e. immediately after a test has
    executed.</p>

    <p>Next we instrument the HTTPRequest with the test being
    executed. This enables any calls through HTTPRequest to be
    monitored by the Grinder. Any other time spent within the script
    will not be recorded by The Grinder. Be careful not to include
    extra script processing within a test; doing so will not give the
    correct statistics. Only test what is required.</p>

    <p>The test itself is next executed which is a HTTP GET to the
    server using our previously constructed test string. Remember -
    these tests execute in a loop for the number of tests we have
    defined, using a random test each time.</p>

<source class="jython">
if string.find(result.getText(), "SUCCESS") &lt; 1:
    grinder.statistics.forLastTest.setSuccess(0)
    writeToFile(result.getText(), testId)
</source>

    <p>On return from the HTTP GET, we check the result for the string
    "SUCCESS". If the test has failed, this value will not be returned
    and the statistics object can be marked as unsuccessful. In the
    case of an unsuccessful test, we write the HTML output to a file
    for later analysis:</p>

<source class="jython">
def writeToFile(text, testId):
    filename = "%s-%d-page-%d.html" % (grinder.processName,
                                       testId,
                                       grinder.runNumber)

    file = open(filename, "w")
    print >> file, text
    file.close()
</source>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Full Script Listing</title>

<source class="jython">
# Send an HTTP request to the server with XML request values

import string
import random
from java.lang import String
from java.net import URLEncoder

from net.grinder.script import Test
from net.grinder.plugin.http import HTTPRequest
from net.grinder.common import GrinderException

tests = {
    "News01"      : Test(1, "News 1 posting"),
    "Sport01"     : Test(2, "Sport 1 posting"),
    "Sport02"     : Test(3, "Sport 2 posting"),
    "Trading01"   : Test(4, "Trading 1 query"),
    "LifeStyle01" : Test(5, "LifeStyle 1 posting"),
}

log = grinder.logger.info
out = grinder.logger.TERMINAL

# Server Properties

SERVER     = "http://serverhost:7001"
URI        = "/myServlet"

class TestRunner:
    def __call__(self):

        for idx in range(len(tests)):

           testId = random.choice(tests.keys())

           log("Reading XML file %s " % testId)

           file = open("./CAAssets/"+testId+".xml", 'r')
           fileStr = URLEncoder.encode(String(file.read()))
           file.close()

           # Send the request to the server
           requestString = "%s%s%s%s" % (SERVER, URI, "?xmldata=", fileStr)
           requestString = string.join(requestString.split(), "")

           grinder.statistics.delayReports = 1
           request = HTTPRequest()
           tests[testId].record(request)

           log("Sending request %s " % requestString)
           result = request.GET(requestString)

           if string.find(result.getText(), "SUCCESS") &lt; 1:
              grinder.statistics.forLastTest.setSuccess(0)
              writeToFile(result.getText(), testId)


# Write the response
def writeToFile(text, testId):
    filename = "%s-%d-page-%d.html" % (grinder.processName,
                                       testId,
                                       grinder.runNumber)
    file = open(filename, "w")
    print >> file, text
    file.close()
</source>

  </section>
</body>
</document>
