<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
    <title>The Console</title>
</header>
<body>
    <figure src="../images/console-screenshot.png" width="900" height="529"
      alt="The Console"/>

    <section>
      <title>Process controls</title>

      <p><em>Start processes</em>, <em>Reset processes</em> and
      <em>Stop processes</em> send signals to Grinder processes that
      are listening. (See <a href="site:properties">
      grinder.receiveConsoleSignals</a>, <a
      href="site:properties">grinder.grinderAddress</a> and <a
      href="site:properties">grinder.grinderPort</a>.)</p>

      <p>Worker processes that are configured to receive console
      signals go through three states:</p>

      <ol>
	<li>Initiated (waiting for a console signal)</li>

	<li>Running (performing tests, reporting to console)</li>

	<li>Finished (waiting for a console signal)</li>
      </ol>

      <p>The <em>Start processes</em> control signals to worker
      processes that they should move into the running state.
      Processes that are already running ignore this signal. Processes
      that are in the finished state exit; the agent process will then
      reread the properties file and launch new worker processes in
      the running state.</p>

      <p>The <em>Reset processes</em> control signals all the worker
      processes to exit. The agent process will then reread the
      properties file and launch new worker processes.</p>

      <p>The <em>Stop processes</em> control signals all processes to
      exit.</p>

      <warning>Warning - unless <a
      href="site:properties">grinder.appendLog</a> is true, new worker
      process logs will overwrite those from previous runs.</warning>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sample controls</title>

      <p>The sample controls determine how the console captures
      reports from the worker processes. capture. It is important to
      understand that these control the console behaviour
      <em>only</em>. For example, they do not adjust the frequency at
      which the worker processes send reports (see <a
      href="site:properties">grinder.reportToConsole.interval</a> for
      that). Additionally, the sample controls do not interact in any
      way with the process controls.</p>

      <p>The slider controls the period at which the console will take
      a <em>sample</em>. This involves adding up all the reports
      received over that sample interval and calculating the TPS as
      (number of transactions that occurred)/(interval length). It is
      also the period at which the console graphs and statistics are
      updated.</p>

      <p>By default, the console discards the first non-zero sample
      period, and starts updating the display and calculating totals
      from the second sample. A non-zero sample period is one in which
      an update from a worker process was received. You can adjust how
      many non-zero sample periods the console ignores before starting
      capture with the <em>ignore samples</em> text field.</p>

      <p>The third control allows you to adjust how many samples the
      console will collect before stopping capture.</p>

      <p>You can also manually start and stop the sampling with the
      <em>Capture statistics</em>/<em>Stop capture</em> control. Use
      the <em>Save statistics</em> control to save the current set of
      statistics to a file.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

