<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>The HTTP Plug-in</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>HTTP plug-in class</title>

      <p>To use the HTTP plug-in, specify:</p>

<source class="text">
grinder.plugin=net.grinder.plugin.http.HttpPlugin
</source>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>HTTP plug-in properties</title>

      <p>This table lists the HTTP plug-in properties that you can set
      in <code>grinder.properties</code> in addition to the <a
      href="site:properties">core properties</a>. You can use the
      TCPSniffer to <a
      href="site:tcpsniffer/HttpPluginSnifferFilter">record</a> HTTP
      plug-in scripts.</p>

      <table>
  <tr>
    <td><code>grinder.test0.parameter.url</code></td>

    <td>The URL to call. The HTTP <code>GET</code> method is
    used unless <code>grinder.test0.parameter.post</code> is
    specified. The contents of the file can be varied using a
    <code>string bean</code>, see this <a
    href="site:gfaq/g2faq/post-and-string-beans">FAQ</a>.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td><code>grinder.test0.parameter.post</code></td>

    <td>Specify a file containing <code>POST</code> data to
    send. The value can be varied using a <a
    href="#string-bean">string bean</a>.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td><code>grinder.test0.parameter.header.name</code></td>

    <td>(Where <code>name</code> can be an arbitrary string).
    Add a <code>name:</code> header to the request with the
    specified value. The value can be varied using a <a
    href="#string-bean">string bean</a>.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td><code>grinder.plugin.parameter.stringBean</code></td>

    <td>Fully qualified class name of a Java bean that can
    generate dynamic strings. See <a href="#string-bean">What's
    a String Bean?</a>.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td><code>grinder.test0.parameter.ok</code></td>

    <td>Fail if the returned page doesn't contain this string.
    The value can be varied using a <a
    href="#string-bean">string bean</a>.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td><code>grinder.test0.parameter.basicAuthenticationRealm</code><br/>
    <code>grinder.test0.parameter.basicAuthenticationUser</code><br/>
    <code>grinder.test0.parameter.basicAuthenticationPassword</code><br/>
    </td>

    <td>Used together, these specify an HTTP BASIC
    authentication header that will be sent with the request. If
    you specify one of these values, you must specify all three.

      <p>Note, the default <a href="#HTTPClient">HTTPClient
      implementation</a> only sends this if challenged by the
      server, as a browser would, and the specified
      basicAuthenticationRealm must match the realm required by
      the WWW-Authenticate header in the challenge. The values
      can be varied using a <a href="#string-bean">string
      bean</a>.</p>
    </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td><code>grinder.plugin.parameter.useCookies</code></td>

    <td>Set to <code>false</code> to disable cookie handling (it
    defaults to <code>true</code>).</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td><code>grinder.plugin.parameter.disablePersistentConnections</code></td>

    <td>Set to <code>true</code> to send a <code>Connection:
    close</code> message with every request. See <a
    href="ext:innovation/httpclient/advanced/pers_con">http://www.innovation.ch/java/HTTPClient/advanced_info.html#pers_con</a>.
    Only works with the default <a href="#HTTPClient">HTTPClient
    implementation</a>. The default is <code>false</code>.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td><code>grinder.plugin.parameter.followRedirects</code></td>

    <td>
      <p>Set to <code>true</code> to automatically follow
      redirects, so you don't have to have additional URLs in
      you scripts. The default is <code>false</code>. You should
      always set this to <code>false</code> for TCPSniffer
      generated scripts.</p>

      <p>If you are using WebLogic Server and Web Application
      form-based authentication you leave this property set to
      false. This is because a redirect request that follows
      authentication contains a key cookie - setting the
      property to <code>true</code> prevents the cookie from
      being picked up by the plug-in.</p>
    </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td><code>grinder.useHTTPClient</code></td>

    <td>Controls which of the <a href="#HTTPClient">two
    different HTTP libraries</a> the HTTP plug-in uses. The
    default value is <code>true</code>, meaning that the
    HTTPClient implementation should be used.</td>
  </tr>
      </table>

      <section id="string-bean">
  <title>What's a String Bean?</title>

  <p>When using the HTTP plug-in, it is often necessary to
  parametrise parts of URLs, POST data, and other request
  strings. The easy way to do this is to use a <em>string
  bean</em> - a Java Bean that returns <code>String</code>s from
  its <code>get</code> methods.</p>

  <p>For example, suppose you wanted to modify the URL
  <code>http://myhost/test.jsp?n=1</code> such that
  <code>n</code> is set to a random number each time? Easy!
  Here's how.</p>

  <ol>
    <li>
      <p>Write a simple bean:</p>

<source class="java">
// MyStringBean.java
package mystuff;

import java.util.Random;

public class MyStringBean {
  private Random m_random = new Random();

  public String getRandomInteger() {
    return Integer.toString(m_random.nextInt());
  }
}
</source>
    </li>

    <li>
      <p>Compile this and put it in your <code>CLASSPATH</code>.
      Then alter your <code>grinder.properties</code> to include
      this line:</p>
<source class="text">
grinder.plugin.parameter.stringBean=mystuff.MyStringBean
</source>
    </li>

    <li>
      <p>Alter the test URL parameter as follows:</p>

<source class="text">
grinder.test0.parameter.url=http://myhost/test.jsp?n=&lt;getRandomInteger&gt;
</source>

    </li>
  </ol>

  <p>The <em><code>&lt;beanMethodName&gt;</code></em> syntax can
  be used in URL strings, <code>POST</code> data files, HTTP
  headers and in OK strings. It must correspond to a
  <code>public</code> method of the string bean that takes no
  parameters and returns a <code>String</code>.</p>

  <p>The HTTP plug-in is relaxed about a partial string bean tag
  matches (for example <code>&lt;notAMethod&gt;</code> or
  <code>&lt;abc&lt;def&gt;xyz&gt;</code>); if it can't find a
  suitable match it simply outputs the literal text. This allows
  string bean tags to be used within XML <code>POST</code> data.
  If you find that your string bean is not invoked when you
  expect it to be, use the <a
  href="site:tcpsniffer">TCPSniffer</a> to find out what is
  actually being sent and check your spelling.</p>

  <p>Each string bean instance is instantiated per thread, and
  maintains its state between invocations. If your bean needs
  additional information regarding the test life cycle (for
  example, to reset a counter and the beginning of a cycle), it
  can implement the
  <code>net.grinder.plugin.http.StringBean</code> interface. See
  the examples in
  <code>net.grinder.plugin.http.example</code>.</p>

  <p>Advanced string beans can implement the
  <code>net.grinder.plugin.http.StringBean</code> and/or
  <code>net.grinder.plugin.http.HTTPClientResponseListener</code>
  interfaces to receive callbacks about the test life cycle. See
  the examples in
  <code>src/net/grinder/plugin/http/example</code>.</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="HTTPClient">
      <title>HTTPClient</title>

      <p>The HTTP plugin has two implementations. The default
      implementation is based on Ronald Tschal&#xE4;r's excellent
      <strong>HTTPClient</strong> library. An alternative
      implementation which uses the JDK's
      <code>HttpURLConnection</code> can also be used, but is
      deprecated and will be removed from The Grinder in a future
      release. If you really want to you can specify that the HTTP
      plug-in should use <code>HttpURLConnection</code> instead of
      HTTPClient:</p>

<source class="text">
grinder.plugin.parameter.useHTTPClient=false
</source>

      <p>I highly recommend the HTTPClient implementation, see below
      for some reasons why. However the HttpURLConnection
      implementation has two features that the HTTPClient
      implementation doesn't. The first feature is an additional
      parameter:</p>

      <table>
  <tr>
    <td><code>grinder.plugin.parameter.useCookiesVersionString</code></td>

    <td>Set to <code>false</code> to remove the
    <code>$Version</code> string from cookies (it defaults to
    true). This is to work around broken (?) JRun 2.3.3.
    behaviour.</td>
  </tr>
      </table>

      <p>The HTTPClient cookie support is damn good, so this probably
      isn't an issue. It will be fixed if it turns out to be a
      problem.</p>

      <p>The second additional feature is the reporting of the
      <em>mean time to first byte</em> statistic in addition to the
      normal total transaction time statistic. This will be supported
      by the HTTPClient implementation in a future release.</p>

      <section>
  <title>HTTPClient versus HttpURLConnection</title>

  <p>HTTPClient has many more features than HttpURLConnection,
  see <a href="ext:innovation/httpclient/urlcon-vs-httpclient">
  http://www.innovation.ch/java/HTTPClient/urlcon_vs_httpclient.html</a>
  for a comparison. I hope to lever features such as proxy
  support, connection timeouts and persistent cookies into
  future versions of The Grinder.</p>

  <p>You can access many HTTPClient features by setting system
  properties. See <a
  href="ext:innovation/httpclient/advanced">http://www.innovation.ch/java/HTTPClient/advanced_info.html</a>
  for a list of properties. For example, you can force
  HTTPClient to use HTTP 1.0 instead of HTTP 1.1 with the
  following parameter:</p>

<source class="text">
grinder.jvm.arguments=-DHTTPClient.forceHTTP_1.0=true
</source>

  <p>One of the key advantages for The Grinder is that
  HTTPClient allows explicit control of connection management,
  whereas HttpURLConnection uses connection pooling "under the
  covers". Because HTTPClient uses extra connections, it may
  appear slower - <a href="site:timing">particularly if the
  client and server are co-hosted</a>. However, its a better
  model of reality (one cycle equals one browser session).</p>

  <p>In my experience, HTTPClient is <em>much</em> more RFC
  compliant, and less buggy than HttpURLConnection.</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="https">
      <title>How do I use HTTPS?</title>

      <p>There are patches available to HTTPClient to work with
      several SSL implementations. See <a
      href="ext:innovation/httpclient/https">http://www.innovation.ch/java/HTTPClient/https.html</a>
      for details. The instructions that follow assume you are using
      JSSE 1.0.3 or later.</p>

      <ol>
  <li>
    <p>If you are using an old JVM (earlier than 1.4.1), you'll need
    to install <a href="ext:oracle/java/jsse-archive">JSSE1.0.3</a>. I
    recommend installing the JSSE as an installed extension for
    simplicity.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p>Download the HTTPClient JSSE patch from <a
    href="ext:innovation/httpclient/jsse-zip">http://www.innovation.ch/java/HTTPClient/JSSE.zip</a></p>

    <p>Extract the class files contained within the zip into a
    directory called HTTPClient, then create a jar containing
    that directory:</p>

<source class="sh">
mkdir HTTPClient; cd HTTPClient
jar xf /download/JSSE.zip
cd ..
jar cf HTTPClient-JSSE.jar HTTPClient
</source>

    <p>Add this jar to the <em>start</em> of your
    <code>CLASSPATH</code> before running The Grinder. Its worth
    reading the file README in JSSE.zip.</p>
  </li>

  <li>You can now use URLs that start with <code>https:</code>
  in your <code>grinder.properties</code>.</li>
      </ol>

      <p>You may well need to create a trust store containing CA
      certificates that sign the server certificate. See the JSSE
      documentation for full details, here's a quick hint:</p>

<source class="sh">
keytool -import -v -keystore ./mycastore -file d:/wls5/myserver/ca.pem
</source>

      <p>You should then add
      <code>-Djavax.net.ssl.trustStore=mycastore</code> to
      <code>grinder.jvm.arguments</code> in your
      <code>grinder.properties</code>. Refer to the JSSE documentation
      for other useful properties. In particular
      <code>-Djavax.net.debug=ssl</code> might come in useful.</p>

      <p>HTTPClient checks that the host name in each request URL
      matches the subject DN field in the certificate. If this isn't
      the case, you might need to add an entry to
      <code>/etc/hosts</code>,
      <code>c:/WINNT40/system32/drivers/etc/</code>, DNS or whatever,
      and then use that hostname in the request URLs.</p>

      <p>The JSSE SSL implementation isn't quick. This should be taken
      into account when comparing round trip times, as a compiled
      browser version is likely to be <em>a lot</em> faster.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>How do I use the HTTPS plug-in? <em>(HttpURLConnection
      implementation only)</em></title>

      <note>This information applies to the deprecated
      HttpURLConnection implementation. For information on using HTTPS
      with the default HTTPClient implementation, see <a
      href="#https">above</a>.</note>

      <ol>
  <li>Install JSSE1.0.3 as described above.</li>

  <li>In your <code>grinder.properties</code>, use the
  HttpsPlugin rather than HttpPlugin:

<source class="text">
grinder.plugin=net.grinder.plugin.http.HttpsPlugin
</source>
  </li>

  <li>You can now use URLs that start with <code>https:</code>
  in your <code>grinder.properties</code>.</li>

  <li>If you want two-way authentication, add the lines like:

<source class="text">
grinder.plugin.parameter.clientCert=./philclient.p12
grinder.plugin.parameter.clientCertPassword=acrobat
</source>

    You can export a P12 certificate from Netscape.
  </li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
