<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document>
<header>
  <title>Contributing</title>
</header>

<body>
  <section id="source">
  <title>The Source</title>

  <p>From September 2011, The Grinder source code and documentation is
  hosted in a <a href="ext:git">Git</a> repository. You can obtain a
  copy from <a href="ext:sourceforge/git">Sourceforge</a>.
  </p>

  <p>Note, the documentation branch (<em>docs</em>) refers to the latest
  released version of The Grinder, and so can lag the Git
  <code>HEAD</code>.</p>

  </section>

  <section>
  <title>What do I need to build The Grinder?</title>

  <p>If you want to build The Grinder from source, you'll need:</p>

  <table class="noborder">
    <tr>
      <td><a href="ext:oracle/java/javase">Java Standard Edition 6 ("Java 6") or higher</a></td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="ext:mvn">Apache Maven 3.0.3</a></td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
  </table>

  <p>Dependencies on third party libraries are managed by Maven.</p>

  </section>

  <section>
  <title>What do I need to test and package The Grinder?</title>

  <p>The following optional packages are necessary to run The Grinder unit
tests.</p>

  <table class="noborder">
    <tr>
      <td><a href="ext:jython">Jython 2.1, 2.5.0, 2.5.1, 2.5.2</a></td>
      <td>to verify The Grinder works with alternative Jython versions</td>
    </tr>
  </table>

  </section>

  <section>
  <title>How to give back</title>

  <p>If you feel you have something worth sharing, please first
  discuss your ideas on the <a
  href="ext:mail/grinder-development">grinder-development list</a>. If
  your ideas develop into code, you can submit patches to this list.
  Patches should be generated using <code>git format-patch -M -B</code>
  against either the latest released version of The Grinder 3, or the
  Git <code>master</code> branch. Patches should also include updates
  to the relevant documentation sources. Please include a statement in
  your email that you, and where appropriate your employer, are happy
  for your work to be distributed under the terms of <a
  href="site:license">The Grinder license</a>.</p>

  <section>
  <title>Coding Standards</title>

  <p>Contributions of Java code should be checked with the
  <a href="ext:findbugs">FindBugs</a> static analysis tool, and pass with no
  warnings. A FindBugs filter file for The Grinder can be found in the
  <code>etc</code> directory.</p>

  <p>I actively track code coverage, and expect full JUnit tests for
  new code. I use <a href="ext:atlassian/clover">Clover</a>; you can get a
  free Clover license for development of The Grinder.</p>

  <p>I have a strong preference for classes that take all the things
  they need as parameters to their constructors (like <a
  href="ext:fowler/constructor-injection">constructor injection</a>),
  and for contracts to be specified in terms of Java interfaces. This
  makes unit testing easier, and forces the developer to think
  about the purpose and contract of each class.</p>

  <p>Please pay attention to the existing coding style of The Grinder.
  There is a <a href="ext:checkstyle">Checkstyle</a> configuration
  file for The Grinder in <code>etc</code> which you should use to
  check the formatting of your code. You can do this using the
  <code>checkstyle:checkstyle</code> Maven goal. Checkstyle helps to
  make the code readable, catches quite a few silly errors, and makes
  applying patches a much nicer experience. Patches that do not pass
  the Checkstyle rules will be rejected.</p>

  </section>

  </section>

  <section id="documentation">
    <title>Documentation help wanted</title>

    <p>Documentation can always be improved. Tutorials and examples from
    users of The Grinder are always welcome. Please mail suggestions,
    corrections, and improvements to the <a href="ext:mail/grinder-development">
    grinder-development@lists.sourceforge.net</a> mailing list.</p>

    <p>The Subversion repository for The Grinder documentation is public. Authors who
    have made valuable contributions can ask for check-in rights via the
    <a href="ext:mail/grinder-development">grinder-development@lists.sourceforge.net</a>
    mailing list.</p>
  </section>

  <section id="translating">
    <title>Internationalisation help wanted</title>

    <p>If you are bilingual you might fancy translating the console
    into a language of your choice. Jose Antonio Zapta Rey did just
    this and produced a Spanish translation.</p>

    <figure src="../images/console-es-g3.png" alt="Console in Spanish"/>

    <p>This translation will be automaically be the default for users
    with their locale set correctly for the Spanish language. If your
    locale is set otherwise and you are curious to try this out,
    specify the Java <code>user.language</code> system property.</p>

<source class="sh">
java -Duser.language="es" net.grinder.Console
</source>

    <p>Bertrand Ave produced a translation for French speaking
    users (<code>user.language="fr"</code>), Huibert Alblas
    produced a German translation (<code>user.language="de"</code>),
    and Italian, Polish, Russian, and Chinese translations have since followed.
    </p>

    <section>
      <title>How to provide or update a translation</title>

      <p>The translation properties files are stored in
      <a href="ext:sourceforge/git/console-resources">
      the source repository</a>. Getting the file directly from the
      repository will make your translation is as up to date as
      possible, and avoid duplicating effort.  The definition of all
      English text used by the console is contained in the
      <code>Console.properties</code> file. Individual translations
      are contained in <code>Console_XX.properties</code> where XX is
      the two letter <a href="ext:iso-639">ISO 639 language
      code</a>. For example, the Spanish translation is contained in
      <code>Console_es.properties</code>. If you want to update an
      existing translation, make a copy of the file. If you want to
      create a new translation, create a new file.</p>

      <p>Use a text editor to edit your file. Existing translations
      will guide you as to which properties you need to translate.
      You should only include properties that have translated text.
      Don't include properties such as <code>scriptTab.image</code>
      that refer to images, or properties that refer to logical names
      such as <code>action.menu</code>.</p>

      <p>To test your file before contributing it, place the file in a
      directory structure matching
      <code>translation/net/grinder/console/swingui/resources</code> and add
      the <code>translation</code> directory to the start of the
      <code>CLASSPATH</code> that you use to start the console. You
      may need to set <code>user.language</code> as described
      above. The Grinder is being actively developed, and you will not be
      able to test new translation properties added since the last
      release without building the latest source from the repository.
      If you can't find the time for this, an untested translation is better
      than no translation.</p>

      <p>Post your translation to the <a
      href="ext:mail/grinder-development">grinder-development
      list</a>, stating the git hash of the revision upon which it was
      based. Please also include a statement that you are happy for
      your work to be distributed under the terms of <a
      href="site:license">The Grinder license</a>.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="dependees">
    <title>Writing software that depends on The Grinder</title>

    <p>There are many projects that build upon, or otherwise complement,
    the features provided by The Grinder. Some of these are referenced from
    the <a href="site:links">links page</a>.
    </p>

    <p>On release, The Grinder jar files are deployed to the <a
    href="ext:sonatype/oss">Sonatype</a> OSS Nexus repository, and
    will be synchronised to <a href="ext:mvn/central">Maven
    Central</a> soon afterwards.</p>

  </section>
</body>
</document>
